<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/</link><description>Recent content on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 17:56:04 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The demarcation problem</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/beliefs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 17:56:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/beliefs/</guid><description>Science is not so much a fixed set of beliefs (e.g. the Earth is a sphere, the stars are distant suns etc.) but rather a process for gaining knowledge using reasoning (in the form of mathematics, simulations etc.) and data to support certain claims. Quoting Boudry, Maarten (2020) Diagnosing Pseudoscience – by Getting Rid of The Demarcation Problem. URL:(accessed 2022-10-31). &amp;hellip;as Thomas Paine put it, because their theories have nothing to do with reality.</description></item><item><title>Culture and societal transformations</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/culture/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 09:59:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/culture/</guid><description>I stumbled upon Why we failed to approve the new Chilean constitution: the need for a cultural transformation this morning while browsing twitter. Quoting:
I cannot stop thinking about Pepe Mujica’s sentence in his documentary, “the most important transformation is not political, but cultural.” We failed to approve the new constitution because we haven’t addressed the need for a cultural transformation that would allow us to negotiate a new set of values with one another.</description></item><item><title>Power laws</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/pareto/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 13:18:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/pareto/</guid><description>Quoting Anderson, Philip W. &amp;ldquo;More is different: broken symmetry and the nature of the hierarchical structure of science.&amp;rdquo; Science 177.4047 (1972): 393-396.:
In closing, I offer two examples from economics of what I hope to have said. Marx said that quantitative differences become qualitative ones, but a dialogue in Paris in the 1920&amp;rsquo;s sums it up even more clearly: FITZGERALD: The rich are different from us. HEMINGWAY: Yes, they have more money.</description></item><item><title>Taking appearances seriously in machine learning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/tas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 18:30:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/tas/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been attempting to kind of distil what are the basic claims made in Taking Appearance Seriously: The Dynamic Way of Seeing in Goethe and European Thought. The authors claim that modern science is locked in the the Cartesian/Lockean tradition, and goes something like this:
Everything has a hidden &amp;ldquo;form&amp;rdquo; (in the neo-platonic sense) and a separate appearance. All we can observe is the appearance. We can use various methods of statistical/mathematical thinking to discover the form from the appearance (this is where ML fits in).</description></item><item><title>Without fanaticism there is no victory</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/religion/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 20:31:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/religion/</guid><description>One of the common tropes in Marxism (or, in fact, most forms of liberalism) is the rational organisation of society. This collective rationality ultimately stems from aggregates of individual rationality, either organised top-down or bottom up. Rationality alone does not suffice for anything it seems, not even building core tech. We need to attach some form of transcendental meaning to anything we do, even if it&amp;rsquo;s technology.</description></item><item><title>We can't have nice things</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/cauchy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 20:22:42 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/cauchy/</guid><description>One of the clearest tweet threads on why self-driving cars are hard is the one below. I do no have anything to add, but that someone should do the simulations and with real simulated features and write a paper about it. It would make for a very entertaining read&amp;hellip;
For years I&amp;#39;ve been claiming that our #AI being based in statistics is not equipped for dealing real world data. That data is most likely fat-tailed, and hence not possible to characterize by sampling.</description></item><item><title>The tyranny of numbers</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/tyranny/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 20:32:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/tyranny/</guid><description>A problem I keep coming back to is one of the first things one notices when trying to analyse social science data; it is hard to come up with any concrete conclusion &amp;ndash; or, conversely, it is easy to make up any story you want, and have your data confirm it. It&amp;rsquo;s trivial to keep adding confounders and claiming that &amp;ldquo;aha&amp;rdquo;, this is confounded by X, which behaves like this and that, which you did not take into account when doing the study.</description></item><item><title>Mysticism and Cybernetics</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mysticyber/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 17:09:56 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mysticyber/</guid><description>I am writing a new paper on economic planning, and it&amp;rsquo;s interesting to observe the kind of mystical fervour certain cybernetic themes arouse. I am not sure why, but my suspicion is that cybernetics was the last effort to do anything &amp;ldquo;AI-ish&amp;rdquo; not serving moneyed interests. We have had like 70 years since these topics were introduced, and they were all more or less incorporated in RL. Their limitations are more than obvious now.</description></item><item><title>An open mind is like a fortress with its gates unbarred and unguarded</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/openmind/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 21:28:49 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/openmind/</guid><description>There is a full list of WH40K quotes here: https://wh40k.lexicanum.com/wiki/Thought_for_the_day_(A_-_H) &amp;ndash; alongside other gems one can find &amp;ldquo;A logical argument must be dismissed with absolute conviction!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;He who allows the alien to live shares its crime of existence&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Hope is the beginning of unhappiness&amp;rdquo;.
The game is obviously satire, but I think the quotes talk to the power of fanaticism. Strong, unmovable beliefs can change the world.</description></item><item><title>Interim ethics and Soul Reaver 2</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/interim/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 07:15:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/interim/</guid><description>The most captivating piece of dialogue I came across in a game is between Kain and Raziel in Soul Reaver 2:
Kain : There&amp;rsquo;s a third option, a monumental secret hidden in your very presence here. But it&amp;rsquo;s a secret you have to discover for yourself. Unearth your destiny, Raziel. It&amp;rsquo;s all laid out for you here. Raziel : You said it yourself, Kain&amp;hellip; there are only two sides to your coin.</description></item><item><title>Sinking ships and the wheel of history</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ships/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 07:22:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ships/</guid><description>Chappo trap house is reviewing Lachmann, Richard. First Class Passengers on a Sinking Ship: Elite Politics and the Decline of Great Powers. Verso Books, 2020. The book uses binary tables to make its arguments &amp;ndash; and it is a pleasure to read. An example is the one below. Notice how we have fewer samples than required to exhaust the search space. What I find interesting is how elite-heavy his account it.</description></item><item><title>Scarcity is the scourge of freedom</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/scarcity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 22:59:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/scarcity/</guid><description>I came across this superb paper: Aronowitz, Stanley. “The Last Good Job in America.” Social Text, no. 51 (1997): 93–108. &amp;ndash; quoting:
&amp;hellip;among others, Robert Spiegelman, Herbert Marcuse, and Murray Bookchin have argued, scarcity is the scourge of freedom and, from the perspective of the rulers, must be artificially repro- duced to maintain the system of domination. Hence, working hours are longer, supervision-call it surveillance-more intense, accidents and injuries more frequent, and wages and salaries lower.</description></item><item><title>Experience and imagination</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/exp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 21:47:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/exp/</guid><description>There is this quote by Rob Pike of Bell Labs (of Plan 9 fame) that &amp;ldquo;Narrowness of experience leads to narrowness of imagination&amp;rdquo;, which epitomises systems thinking. Pike complains about the loss of diversity of thought in system design (everything is more or less Unix), claiming that a new generation will come that would have very narrow experiences when it comes to computing ideas. He probably accepted this inevitable moved on to help design GO.</description></item><item><title>Technology and labour in the Roman world</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/techlabo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 07:11:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/techlabo/</guid><description>I am reading Robert M. Grant&amp;rsquo;s Augustus to Constantine: The Rise and Triumph of Christianity in the Roman World
A superb quote from the book, that links directly to how we conceive technology today is the following:
Generally speaking, technology either military or civil did not flourish in antiquity. Perhaps the existence of slavery blocked technological advance. Another cause is suggested by a story about Vespasian. Offered an invention for lifting stone columns at Rome, he rewarded the inventor but refused to use to the device, stating that he had to &amp;ldquo;feed the poor&amp;rdquo; by providing employment.</description></item><item><title>Blind faith</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/faith/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 09:29:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/faith/</guid><description>Religious studies have a quite a lot to say on the world around us, and progress more specifically. In an article termed When Prophecy Fails and Faith Persists: A Theoretical Overview, one can read the same lesson we find in Kuhn&amp;rsquo;s scientific revolutions book. It&amp;rsquo;s hard for people to change their minds, and religious movements that fail to predict the future can thrive as long as they keep proselytising. Quoting:</description></item><item><title>Alchemy and AI</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/alch/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 20:49:27 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/alch/</guid><description>There is this legendary paper by Hubert Dreyfus; it&amp;rsquo;s a critique on AI written back in 1965. Quite a bit of what is in the paper would not make sense today (as we have somewhat addressed the games and language challenges), but I think the comment that stands out is:
Alchemists were so successful in distilling quicksilver from what seemed to be dirt, that after several hundred years of fruitless effort to convert lead into gold they still re- fused to believe that on the chemical level one cannot transmute metals.</description></item><item><title>Democracy and reinforcement learning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/democracy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 16:25:13 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/democracy/</guid><description>In the age-old battle between representative vs direct democracy, two systems stand out. In representative democracy, it seems range voting, where each candidate is given a score from 0 to 99 by each voter, has certain desirable properties. In (direct) democracy, the way Aristotle describes it in Politics, no elections take place but a group of qualified candidates (which can presumably be the whole population) is subsampled randomly. The argument for random subsampling is that people tend to vote for wealthy and famous individuals, so getting someone to represent the &amp;ldquo;common man&amp;rdquo; requires just picking someone in random and giving them an admin post.</description></item><item><title>Cosmic transformation and mobile phones</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/cosmotrans/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 06:13:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/cosmotrans/</guid><description>Mobile phones act as a stigmatic, always on view of the world; this can be easily observed when visiting a foreign city. Getting bus routes, calling taxis and finding where to eat all become trivial. Given the amount of people that would have visited each place, there is probably a healthy amount of exploration to cover everything (and a good degree of exploitation, top tripadvisor restaurants have queues outside). The phone radically changes behaviour &amp;ndash; you no longer need to start an exploration/exploitation process everytime from scratch when you are in new place &amp;ndash; previous visitors have collectively done it for you, so you play the e-greedy game with reasonably good initial estimates.</description></item><item><title>Dreams and lies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/sandman/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 08:29:38 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/sandman/</guid><description>Neil Gaiman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;the sandman&amp;rdquo; is one of the first comic books I&amp;rsquo;ve read (early in my 20s). I thoroughly enjoy the Neflix adaptation; episode 5 does a great play on lies and dreams. If you remove dreams, all that remains are the basic instincts (sex and death).
What makes the whole endeavour interesting is the link between AI, failed prophecies and the post 1980s world. We need dreams to keep moving, but what happens when dreams are served on a platter?</description></item><item><title>Happiness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/happy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 10:09:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/happy/</guid><description>There is this anecdote that John Stuart Mill used to ask adherents of certain political theories what immediate benefit they would gain if their favourite ideas were enacted. I am not sure this is the right way to frame politics (or technology or science or anything else). The active pursuit of happiness is deeply individual, and I strongly agree with Castoriadis when he claims that (in The Imaginary Institution of Society):</description></item><item><title>More failed prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/morefailure/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2022 05:50:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/morefailure/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s astonishing how many failed prophecies we had since the 90s. Transhumanism and Crypto are two prominent examples, but the likes of AI are not far away.
The post-soviet world is struggling to find meaning, create goals or generally go anywhere. The collective west has been living on lies for 2K years now, as Paul&amp;rsquo;s cosmic transformation is still not here, but somehow we keep going. We subside on a steady diet of propaganda, lies and half truths, fed to us by everyone who has any media access.</description></item><item><title>Should we still wear sunscreen?</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/crisis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 20:00:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/crisis/</guid><description>There is this quote, in the now legendary Advice, like youth, probably just wasted on the young that goes to show how certain truths of the post 1945 consensus are not with us any more:
Accept certain inalienable truths: Prices will rise. Politicians will philander. You, too, will get old. And when you do, you&amp;rsquo;ll fantasize that when you were young, prices were reasonable, politicians were noble and children respected their elders.</description></item><item><title>Ghost quitting</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gquiting/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 19:50:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gquiting/</guid><description>Forbes has an article on ghost quitting. In my life before-becoming-an-academic, I remember having discussions about work and quite often being surprised by coworkers claiming that they have nothing else to spend their time on but work.
It might be bizarre, but I still find meaning in trying to beat games.</description></item><item><title>A fancy typewriter</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/typewriter/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 13:42:11 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/typewriter/</guid><description>I had a kind of &amp;ldquo;take a step back and look at the bigger picture&amp;rdquo; revelation today &amp;ndash; it should be obvious but 99% of all of my computer activity is text. Most tools that I use are there to help with the better editing of text; I code, communicate through e-mails and web forms/chat, I write papers.</description></item><item><title>Experience</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/experience/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 22:47:18 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/experience/</guid><description>I was watching the video below by Christopher Isham &amp;ndash; not sure why he does not respond directly to the fundamental problem of religion; quite a few of us are unable to feel or experience any religious reality. I would be happy to accept personal revelations as facts, but there aren&amp;rsquo;t any.</description></item><item><title>Newton's prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/newton/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 07:19:13 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/newton/</guid><description>Newton is well known for his alchemical and theological writings. There is a table in https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/593608.Isaac_Newton, a biography of Newton which I read almost 20 years ago, which summarises Neuton&amp;rsquo;s prophecies. They were apparently derived from a close reading of the Bible, and not by any form of revelation. It&amp;rsquo;s not clear to me how he came up with these dates, or if the table has any validity at all. Another set of dates is reported here: https://www.</description></item><item><title>Dilbert</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/dilbert/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 20:07:35 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/dilbert/</guid><description>One of my favourite comic strips is Dilbert &amp;ndash; his HR takes are insanely good &amp;ndash; see here: https://dilbert.com/strip/2022-07-15. The most fundamental line of thought in AI is the direct link between intelligence and agency, and Dilbert is making fun of the typical game NPC, someone with no real role in the world apart from just existing. Acting with purpose is also one of the fundamental tenets of liberalism, which poses a conception of humanity as agents in a cosmic game.</description></item><item><title>Welcome to the desert of the real</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/desert/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 14:01:46 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/desert/</guid><description>One of the most astonishing facts about new media is how much their content is dedicated on commenting other media. Commentary on games, commentary on people playings games, commentary on people watching people playing games etc. We kind of need a measure for this &amp;ndash; something like &amp;ldquo;depth of hyperreality&amp;rdquo;. A documentary is level 0 hyperreal, a movie about the actual event the documentary is depicting level 1, two dudes on twitter watching the documentary level 2 etc.</description></item><item><title>Dawn of time</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/timeline/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 16:23:17 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/timeline/</guid><description>I was searching for a timeline of world events, and I stumbled upon this: https://www.southampton.ac.uk/~cpd/history.html. It&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;Timeline of human evolution and cultural development&amp;rdquo;, as it&amp;rsquo;s author would describe it, and it&amp;rsquo;s one of the most useful resources on the topic I&amp;rsquo;ve seen. I&amp;rsquo;ve used this script here to extract the relevant tables into CSV format for future processing.
I.COSMOLOGICAL_ANTECEDENTS_ II._HUMAN_ANCESTRY_AND_EVOLUTION__1._Evolution_of_life_on_Earth II._HUMAN_ANCESTRY_AND_EVOLUTION__2._Human_evolution III._CULTURAL_DEVELOPMENT__3._Hunter-gatherer_nomads III._CULTURAL_DEVELOPMENT__4._Agricultural_farming_and_settlements III._CULTURAL_DEVELOPMENT__5._Empires_and_conquests III._CULTURAL_DEVELOPMENT__6._Scientific_Revolution III._CULTURAL_DEVELOPMENT__7._Industrial_Revolution III._CULTURAL_DEVELOPMENT__8._Technological_Revolution IV._PLANETARY_MANAGEMENT__9._Sustainability_Revolution</description></item><item><title>Planning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/planning/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 22:50:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/planning/</guid><description>The market, as an abstraction of how we should live our lives, has emerged so victorious that even the thought of minor governmental interventions sounds the alarms of heresy. There is one arrow of time, and that is one of more liberalism, i.e. more market as the solution to everything, no other thoughts needed. Yet the tide is turning, and has been turning for a number of years, but without much in the process of actual results.</description></item><item><title>Soviet computing history</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/sovietcomp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 00:32:07 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/sovietcomp/</guid><description>I am a big fan of personal/home computing, and it&amp;rsquo;s a pity that IBM PC clones dominated the market to such an extent that we are left with no alternatives (except, perhaps, the apple lines). It&amp;rsquo;s also rather interesting that US dominance was so complete, that no other country managed to to maintain local variants. I also wonder how much of it was down to resources/economics or technical capacity. The soviets would have to overhaul their whole economic system if they were to introduce computers successfully.</description></item><item><title>All is matter in motion</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/matter/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2022 23:30:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/matter/</guid><description>Dialectics is somewhat similar to multi-agent learning (or just multi-agent systems, without any learning), possibly combined with simulation based inference (i.e. you ground the models with data). Let&amp;rsquo;s say you actually get to do the perfect simulation, you understand the all the laws of motion (i.e. the dynamics) of the system you are modelling in detail. Let&amp;rsquo;s also say you have fully uncovered every sensible variable that goes into this system.</description></item><item><title>Machine-readable bibles</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bibles/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 10:08:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bibles/</guid><description>I was looking today for machine-readable bibles &amp;ndash; apparently tons of them are here: https://www.crosswire.org/sword/modules/ModDisp.jsp?modType=Bibles and there is a python library to process them here: https://pypi.org/project/pysword/. I was surprised how long it took me to actually find these resources &amp;ndash; I was expecting that a google search would reveal the truth (:P), but nope&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Warhammer 40K: Chaos Gate</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/wh40cg/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 22:31:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/wh40cg/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing quite a bit of Chaos Gate lately (whenever I find the time that is), and I realised I can&amp;rsquo;t beat the final boss. I blitzed through the game recycling a squad of four marines, never levelled up anybody else, and I don&amp;rsquo;t have any mid-game saves. Which means in order to complete the game, I need to go back and start again, something I really don&amp;rsquo;t have the patience for.</description></item><item><title>The Romans</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/romans/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 11:24:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/romans/</guid><description>Beyond the roads and the sanitation, the most enduring Roman legacy must be the concept of property over men, things and animals &amp;ndash; a definition of self based on what you own.</description></item><item><title>Farmers</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/farmers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 08:31:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/farmers/</guid><description>One of the downsides of the western fixation on ruling using the purely ideological means of finance/marketing (i.e. numbers on a computer and propaganda) is the fragility of the whole system. BBC runs an article here https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-61958468 on farmers decreasing food output. I find it unbelievable that the collective west is so disinterested in actual production. Supply chains have half-collapsed, gas and oil pipelines are running dry, but the elite priorities keep being the same (i.</description></item><item><title>Grounding large language models</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/grounding/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 12:51:51 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/grounding/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve came across this paper: Mapping Language Models to Grounded Conceptual Spaces while searching for methods to address the problem of grounding large language models. Seems like the general approach is to feed the model data post-training. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting, as it implies that you can learn from purely mental constructs link them to reality later on.</description></item><item><title>Theodicy and evil gods</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/theod/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 12:15:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/theod/</guid><description>I was reading this morning Law, Stephen. &amp;ldquo;The evil-god challenge.&amp;rdquo; Religious Studies 46.3 (2010): 353-373. and Stein, Edward. &amp;ldquo;God, the demon, and the status of theodicies.&amp;rdquo; American Philosophical Quarterly 27.2 (1990): 163-167..
What is being claimed, more or less, is that one can create negative theodicies (i.e. why the universe is ruled/has been created by an evil deity) as easily as positive ones. It looks to me that the problem dissolves if you just accept that the universe/God/whatever you want to call it has no inherent moral position (or that its moral position is evolving, see Jung&amp;rsquo;s Answer to Job).</description></item><item><title>Flowers for Algernon</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/flowers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 21:24:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/flowers/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve just finished reading Flowers for Algernon &amp;ndash; picked it up from a thread in hacker news &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s such a good read. The style of writing changing throughout the book makes for a great literally vehicle &amp;ndash; Charlie starts writing phonetically (i.e. the same way I write Greek&amp;hellip;), moves on to super-proper-scientist style (following a &amp;ldquo;smartification&amp;rdquo; procedure) and finally falls back to his original style as he gradually reverts back.</description></item><item><title>Simpson's paradox and the horrors of unobserved confounders</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/simpson/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 18:46:56 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/simpson/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s assume you have collected data from a hospital, where some patients are given a medicine and some are not. No experimental procedure was followed, you just collected whatever was out there and you want to check if taking the medicine causes improvements in health. With a bit of notational abuse, you want to check the effect of $T \rightarrow Y$. $T$ can be either 0 or 1 (whether someone was treated or not using the medicine), while $Y$ is a measurement of life quality &amp;ndash; the higher the better.</description></item><item><title>Cookie cutter data science</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ccds/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 10:00:07 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ccds/</guid><description>I &amp;rsquo;ve recently discovered https://github.com/drivendata/cookiecutter-data-science/ &amp;ndash; an effort to standardise the pipeline of a data science project. The practices proposed seem ideal to me &amp;ndash; from a very sane directory structure to discussing makefiles as project pipeline DAGs.
Not sure how I managed to survive using completely custom project templates for each project. In fact, I will argue, one should go ahead and automate the whole report/presentation generation pipeline. There aren&amp;rsquo;t that many data science patterns anyway (let&amp;rsquo;s say regression/classification/causal inference/time-series analysis/arbitrary optimisation), so it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that hard.</description></item><item><title>Natural language interfaces for the command line and privacy</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/llmcmd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 06:15:54 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/llmcmd/</guid><description>Microsoft released a natural language interface for the command line (https://github.com/microsoft/Codex-CLI), while a past effort can been seen here: https://github.com/tom-doerr/zsh_codex. What I find worrying is that there is currently no way of using a local model &amp;mdash; these services do remote calls. Which means that you are bound to call OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s APIs, which pretty much guarantees loss of privacy. It looks like alternatives are doing much on the privacy front &amp;ndash; see here: https://www.</description></item><item><title>Mage: the themes</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 17:33:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</guid><description>I listen to podcasts mostly when I drive; I&amp;rsquo;ll compile a list at some point, but my top game-y podcast is definitely this: https://magethepodcast.com/
Mage is one of the most idealistic games you can play. There is no &amp;ldquo;concrete&amp;rdquo; reality, and the main theme of the game is one of self-discovery: you can be whatever you want to be. It flies on the face of my beliefs about the world, but the idea of changing the universe through thought is at the very least seductive.</description></item><item><title>Vale and atom</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/vale/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 10:54:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/vale/</guid><description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to get atomic-vale to work in atom (the editor). Took me a while; on top of a working vale installation, you need to install the linter plugins. From the command line do:
apm install linter The functionality vale provides is exceptionally good, and I am surprised I haven&amp;rsquo;t heard of this before &amp;ndash; I first read about it in hacker news post.</description></item><item><title>Large language models - GPT-3 this time</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 07:26:17 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp2/</guid><description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve started playing with GPT-3 this morning, posing the same questions I&amp;rsquo;ve asked GPT-J. Seems like the answers are much more coherent. For default configuration parameters I get reasonable stuff, but the model has no concept if something is real or not and makes things up:
&amp;ndash; Q: How do I make steel?
A: There are many ways to make steel. The most common method is to start with pig iron.</description></item><item><title>Crypto and paper money</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/crypto/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 22:29:57 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/crypto/</guid><description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve never managed to get my head around Web3 and crypto. What&amp;rsquo;s the value beyond creating Ponzi schemes and bubbles that paper money does not solve? The Canadian trucker&amp;rsquo;s case kind of proved that if the state does not want you transact, you don&amp;rsquo;t. Paper money is anonymous, easy to use and exchange, and needs very little training to use. More on this here: https://web3isgoinggreat.com/</description></item><item><title>Large language models</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 22:22:42 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp/</guid><description>I really don&amp;rsquo;t get all that hype around large language models. I can understand their uses in NLP (and their superb transfer learning powers), but people are treating them like the end-goal of AI. I might be biased, but they don&amp;rsquo;t look that smart to me &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve tried this one here: https://6b.eleuther.ai/. You get different results based on what parameters you use, but:
Model with top-p = 1.0, temperature = 0 (i.</description></item><item><title>Labour theory of value through the lens of reinforcement learning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 07:09:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</guid><description>One of the popular online debates has been on the usefulness of the labour theory of value (LTV). I&amp;rsquo;ll attempt to give LTV a reinforcement learning (RL) spin (that&amp;rsquo;s how I understand it anyway) which should hopefully clarify things a bit. I&amp;rsquo;ll also abuse notation.
Imagine a scenario where an agent (an abstraction of a capitalist, firm, upper management etc) has access to the following at every time step $t$:</description></item><item><title>Goodhart’s Law and AI</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/goodheart/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 14:18:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/goodheart/</guid><description>OpenAI has a blog post here &amp;ndash; quoting from the article:
Goodhart’s law famously says: “When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.” Although originally from economics, it’s something we have to grapple with at OpenAI when figuring out how to optimize objectives that are difficult or costly to measure. It’s often necessary to introduce some proxy objective that’s easier or cheaper to measure, but when we do this, we need to be careful not to optimize it too much.</description></item><item><title>She was a phantom of delight</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 20:41:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</guid><description>William Wordsworth&amp;rsquo;s poem &amp;ldquo;She Was a Phantom of Delight&amp;rdquo; has gotten a new life through netflix third edition of &amp;ldquo;Love, Death and Robots&amp;rdquo;. The specific quote is:
And now I see with eye serene The very pulse of the machine; A Being breathing thoughtful breath, A Traveller between life and death; I originally thought the poem was about some kind of occult revelation the author had, but apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a love poem to his wife!</description></item><item><title>Financial times and workers' power</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 23:26:22 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</guid><description>The FT has published an excellent article Class war &amp;gt; rate hikes &amp;ndash; which concludes with:
In other words, inflation will subside, not because it’s necessarily transitory, but because workers don’t have the power to make it stick around.
What surprises me is how openly this is discussed. Instead of the &amp;ldquo;the euthanasia of the rentier&amp;rdquo;, we got the death of labour &amp;ndash; see the massive losses predicted by OECD below:</description></item><item><title>Coding the matrix</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/cm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 19:40:11 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/cm/</guid><description>I thoroughly admire efforts to turn mathematics into code &amp;ndash; in the legacy of Coding the Matrix. A new book is being released on the topic of Logic: Mathematical Logic through Python. Proof assistants (the likes of Lean) are being continuously developed and becoming more and more mainstream by the hour. I am pretty sure developments in these fronts will revolutionise the teaching of mathematics, making them accessible to whole groups of hobbyists, the same way that autodiff revolutionised ML.</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky III</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 21:16:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</guid><description>Rodney Stark in his book The Rise of Christianity, attempts to estimate the number of Christians per year, and comes up with a some figures that point to exponential growth. Bart Ehrman in the Triumph of Christianity disputes the numbers a bit, but again comes up with exponential growth figures. Incidently, Kautsky in his Foundations of Christianity discusses numbers, but mostly to claim that the Acts are exaggerating (i.e. the numbers are wrong :P).</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky II</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 18:01:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</guid><description>The debate between Kautsky and Lenin can be traced on/attributed to the revolutionary potential of the global north:
&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;Such is the position both in France and in Great Britain. Comrade Crispien does not regard the split like a Communist, but quite in the spirit of Kautsky, who is supposed to have no influence. Then Crispien went on to speak of high wages. The position in Germany, he said, is that the workers are quite well off compared with the workers in Russia or in general, in the East of Europe.</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 11:56:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading Mike Macnair&amp;rsquo;s Revolutionary Strategy: Marxism and the challenge of left unity, and it occurred to me there is a whole world out there of ideas and topics that could be helped by more formal analysis, and by that I mean a more rigorous approach to quantify the outcomes of each topic, the parameters that would go in it and the debates that it would spark. As a start, one can take the the Erfurt programme and start doing a formal/data science analysis on each constituent part of the programme.</description></item><item><title>Working remotely</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/remotework/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 21:32:40 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/remotework/</guid><description>A number of businesses seem to be enforcing a 5-days-a-week-back-to-the-office policy, and obviously some high profile resignations have taken place. Looking at the products I use, they seem to be designed by companies that had a remote work policy even before the pandemic, and somehow I doubt this is an accident.</description></item><item><title>The spirit of the interwebs</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/interwebs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 08:07:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/interwebs/</guid><description>There is a whole trend (and I think my website falls right into it) of 90&amp;rsquo;s/00&amp;rsquo;s tech nostalgia. Quite a few of us feel that the implicit promises of an interconnected world were broken and we need to go back to the prophets. A quick guide for creating your own website the same way you would do it 15 years ago is this one: Web revival. I like the goals of these movements, I am not sure I am convinced with the approach the author is taking.</description></item><item><title>The brick bible</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bb/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 07:38:12 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bb/</guid><description>I have two go-to websites when I need a quick, cheap laugh &amp;ndash; the first is one is the Brick Bible. The author/artist takes some of the more controversial parts of scripture and renders them (with commentary) to Lego scenes. The second website is the comment section of Motley Crue youtube videos (&amp;ldquo;Grills, grills, grills&amp;rdquo;).</description></item><item><title>Neats vs scruffies vs money</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/neats/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 06:05:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/neats/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve stumbled upon &amp;ldquo;What is the well dressed educator wearing now?&amp;rdquo;, an AI education article written in 1982, through a twitter thread. The article can be summed up as a commentary on whether one should pursue theoretical methods vs a more experimental approach (i.e. neats vs scruffies) and has been done to death since the article was written, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have much new to say. What astonished me is the actual focus on education.</description></item><item><title>Big data</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bigdata/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 09:31:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bigdata/</guid><description>Most interesting problems I have encountered in my real-life expeditions involve small data. Big data seems to me like a problem devised by certain tech companies and picked up as a trend by people that don&amp;rsquo;t need it, forcing them to use tools of extreme complexity, and as a result delaying project deployment.</description></item><item><title>Openspiel</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/openspiel/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 17:26:46 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/openspiel/</guid><description>I make use of the common data science frameworks for my everyday work (sklearn, pandas, tensorflow, seaborn and the like). For game-specific stuff I find Openspiel indispensable. It does everything in a very nice API &amp;ndash; from standard RL methods to LP solvers for normal form games to integration with a ton of languages.</description></item><item><title>Elites and class</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 11:53:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</guid><description>Not sure if this is Foucault&amp;rsquo;s fault or just a random historical trend, but I see more and more posts defining class not on material conditions (i.e. on the number of assets you own, amount of sex you have easy access to, disposable income, free time) but on cultural aspects (i.e. the way you sound when you talk, the kind of work you do). This is particularly prevalent among right-wing bloggers; somehow the idle classes have decided that the elites are overworked middle-class professionals and art school graduates.</description></item><item><title>Observational data and politics</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gorbi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 11:18:25 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gorbi/</guid><description>In the age old debate between socialism vs capitalism (the really existing ones, not whatever idealised versions are theoretically possible) empirical studies are sorely lacking. The debate is somewhat poisoned from the outset, as it does not help that people tend to use the word socialism to mean anything from the smallest welfare state to a fully planned economy, but let&amp;rsquo;s confine ourselves to USSR and friends for the scope of this discussion.</description></item><item><title>Eclipse Phase and optimism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 09:42:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</guid><description>The politics of eclipse phase (the game) play nicely as an exploration of a post-scarcity world, where humanity struggles to come to terms with the widespread availability of futuristic tech (makers, full AIs, full body augmentations), but material constraints are mostly not there. Similar themes emerge in Peter Frase&amp;rsquo;s four futures essay. Two binary variables (scarcity and equality) are flipped to create four different potential futures. What is interesting to me is that 10 years ago writers on the left were seriously discussing the prospects of a post-scarcity world.</description></item><item><title>Games and will appropriation</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 08:05:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</guid><description>I often wonder whether the fact that games were generally thought of as the quintessential analogue of intelligence is just due to their clear links with liberalism; you have an environment and you have agents that try to maximise some notion of reward in that environment. Life seems radically different (no clear rewards, no environmental resets, no fixed set of actions, no clear transition function), but most games provide a good abstraction for a competitive universe.</description></item><item><title>Blade runner's soundtrack</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/br/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 20:38:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/br/</guid><description>The composer of Blade Runner&amp;rsquo;s soundtrack, Vangelis, died a couple of days ago. I cannot think of a more iconic cyberpunk soundtrack then the score of the original 1982 film. As an interesting side fact, the story of the film is set to take place in 2019. It&amp;rsquo;s 2022 and still no androids&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Automation keeps being predicted</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/autom/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 06:42:54 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/autom/</guid><description>Automation fears in the 50s, found on twitter, see https://twitter.com/abenanav/status/1526854505136021505
McKinsey (the consultancy) has a job automation chart here, posted in 2016. There seems to be a lingering fear of automation, as this old New York Time article, amply named &amp;ldquo;Automation Puts Industry on Eve of Fantastic Robot Era; Its Effect on Workers Spurs Unions&amp;rsquo; Drive for Annual Wage&amp;rdquo; seems to imply. Notice how McKinsey speculates that managers are secure from automation, though I doubt this is for the right reasons.</description></item><item><title>In praise of idleness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/praise/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 07:02:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/praise/</guid><description>Early in my career, over a break, I approached a co-worker of mine and complained that all of my life&amp;rsquo;s problems were due to my relationship with work. I had watched Office Space the day before, still one of my favourite movies, and almost shed tears of joy seeing that others understood the very same concept, that most of the time we spend on work is meaningless. To my surprise I got back an answer along the lines of &amp;ldquo;what else is there to do in life?</description></item><item><title>Gnostic vs Orthodox</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:33:32 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</guid><description>Philip K. Dick&amp;rsquo;s Valis contains quite a bit of commentary that I find fundamental in understanding gnostic thought. Dick, in his interpretation of Gnosticism, points to an intellectual error for the fall of man (and hence our short lives of toil, pain and labour) rather than the usual orthodox position of moral failure. Interestingly enough, Dick created his own gnostic mythology (which reads like a modern version of the already bizarre gnostic cosmogony, replacing gods with aliens).</description></item><item><title>Virtuals vs Reals</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/va/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:25:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/va/</guid><description>An essay that has been making rounds since it was published is N.S. Lyons&amp;rsquo; Reality Honks Back. It discusses Canadian truckers and the divide between &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; workers (which make use of real-world tools tools) and &amp;ldquo;virtual&amp;rdquo; workers (which deal primarily in information). It contains a flawed effort to link the whole divide to Gnosticism &amp;ndash; it astonishes me that the only modern author that somehow got the Gnostics was P.K. Dick in Valis &amp;ndash; but beyond that the whole argument is very convincing.</description></item><item><title>Measures and fairness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 06:58:18 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mm/</guid><description>A superb article popped in my twitter feed called Measurement and Fairness. The article, as the title implies, deals with the imaginary quantities (e.g. teacher quality) and how operationalising them via actual measurements is where the problem of using metrics (I use the word interchangeably with &amp;ldquo;measures&amp;rdquo;) lies; in terms closer to AI/statistics, how to you link latent variables with observed variables. What strikes me is how fragile the notion of latent variable creation is; one can create whatever metric/measure they want, operationalise it in whatever way they think suits them and use enough force and propaganda to reshape the world according to their fiction.</description></item><item><title>Measures tend to become targets</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/metrics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 09:34:45 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/metrics/</guid><description>Most complaints about gaming a system can be traced back to Goodhart&amp;rsquo;s law, i.e. &amp;ldquo;when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure&amp;rdquo;. In the most trivial of scenarios, let us imagine that an oversight institution is created to measure the quality of teaching, and they come up with &amp;ldquo;average GPA&amp;rdquo;, which takes the mean of all student GPAs at a certain school. The minute this is measured and compiled in a table, someone will start ranking schools according to average GPA.</description></item><item><title>Adversus ludii, adversus ludos</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 16:15:06 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</guid><description>Quick self-bio I entered AI through games; I&amp;rsquo;ve started my PhD thinking roughly that if we manage to solve poker (or more generally, games of imperfection and/or incompleteness), we will manage to more or less solve the problem of AI; solving the problem of AI meant solving the problem of labour. Nobody would have to work, because machines would do all &amp;ndash; just need to solve &amp;ldquo;the problem of games&amp;rdquo; and all we would end up doing is playing games.</description></item><item><title>The comedic value of reviews</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:20:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</guid><description>I often find reviews of higher comedic value than the actual content that is being reviewed. As a kid I used to laugh to the point of tears reading music reviews, and as an adult (?) I still find stuff like Chapo Trap House&amp;rsquo; Wolf Warrior Movie Review eerily funny. Not sure how popular the genre of &amp;ldquo;imaginary reviews&amp;rdquo; (Stanislaw Lem might have popularised it with &amp;ldquo;A Perfect Vacuum&amp;rdquo;) actually is, but I can easily imagine a version where non-existent movies, poems, books, music and the like are reviewed, purely for a good laugh.</description></item><item><title>For and against liberalism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:15:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</guid><description>I was listening to General Intellect Unit&amp;rsquo;s latest episode on my way to work. They discuss &amp;ldquo;Designs for the Pluriverse&amp;rdquo;, by Arturo Escobar. I think their commentary on individualism vs traditionalism is spot on. The response to the modern problem of being alone, alienated and having lost your soul is obviously becoming part of a welcoming community; in contrast, idolising traditional societies seems to me to be a symptom of excessive alienation.</description></item><item><title>Red plenty</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/red_plenty/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:47:46 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/red_plenty/</guid><description>There is this online 12 year old discussion between Spufford and Cockshott on non-market economies and what-could-have-been in the USSR. Even if we could plan the economy to perfection, and this is a big if, I am not convinced it would lead to the kind of freedom most socialists have in mind. Ultimately, human salvation lies in the conditions of production, or as Aristotle would put it in his oft-quoted passage &amp;ldquo;There is only one condition in which we can imagine managers not needing subordinates, and masters not needing slaves.</description></item><item><title>First century sexuality</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:39:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</guid><description>There seems to be a period in the Roman world where all forms of sexuality that were not meant for procreation were frowned upon. The middle Stoics, early Christians, the Epicureans (yes&amp;hellip;), the Manichaeans views on sex can be summed up as &amp;ldquo;better to be avoided, if not do sparingly&amp;rdquo;. In early Christianity, there is ample evidence in the mainstream gospels (e.g. check Matthew and the sermon on the mount), supporting text (e.</description></item><item><title>D&amp;D/Warhammer 40K</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 08:36:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</guid><description>Since I don&amp;rsquo;t get to play tabletop that much (or at all) these days, I substitute with Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 and WH40K: Chaos Gate. Good enough, but obviously far away from the real thing&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Surveillance</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/surv/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 05:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/surv/</guid><description>The EU and UK governments are desperate for our data, and this has been the case for a while. I have no idea what they plan to do with it (most people&amp;rsquo;s lives are super boring, what kind of political dissent are they looking for?), but Briar, Matrix and Signal seem reasonable, sane alternatives.</description></item><item><title>Failed prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Sanctify them in the truth&amp;rdquo; (John 17:17) Tesla (the car business) recently published a video of its AI day giving a tour de force of modern artificial intelligence (AI) methods. From monte carlo tree search to simulation-based reasoning, Tesla is throwing every modern technique to the problem of self driving cars, coupled with possibly some of the best research scientists and engineers in the business. Yet, somehow, this is not enough; as another video mocking Tesla for its inability to produce a self-driving car points out, the promise of real-world AI delivering anything that would resemble its science fiction counterpart is astoundingly far.</description></item><item><title>Moving to Hugo</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/my-first-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 12:28:47 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/my-first-post/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to move my personal website to Hugo. Took a bit of time, but all good in the end</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://ssamot.me/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/about/</guid><description>Working hard&amp;hellip;
I am a senior lecturer in data science &amp;ndash; see here for my institutional website. My research focuses on broader AI themes; I&amp;rsquo;ve started as a game AI researcher, but my interests have since drifted towards out-of-distribution generalisation, robustness and causal inference, though I still maintain a healthy passion for games. I also enjoy thinking how to build new societal institutions and have a general fascination with religion.</description></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://ssamot.me/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/contact/</guid><description>For work related stuff you can e-mail me at my UoE address, for anything personal feel free to contact me at my personal address.</description></item><item><title>Publications</title><link>https://ssamot.me/publications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/publications/</guid><description>You can find most of my (academic) publications under my Google scholar profile.
[1] Husam Quteineh, Spyridon Samothrakis, and Richard Sutcliffe. Enhancing task-specific distillation in small data regimes through language generation. In Proceedings of the 29th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, pages 5955--5965, 2022. [2] Shaaba Lotun, Veronica&amp;nbsp;M Lamarche, Spyridon Samothrakis, Gillian&amp;nbsp;M Sandstrom, and Ana Matran-Fernandez. Parasocial relationships on youtube reduce prejudice towards mental health issues. Scientific Reports, 12(1):1--13, 2022. [3] Spyridon Samothrakis, Ana Matran-Fernandez, Umar Abdullahi, Michael Fairbank, and Maria Fasli.</description></item></channel></rss>