<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/</link><description>Recent content on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 21:24:21 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Flowers for Algernon</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/flowers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 21:24:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/flowers/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve just finished reading Flowers for Algernon &amp;ndash; picked it up from a thread in hacker news &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s such a good read. The style of writing changing throughout the book makes for a great literally vehicle &amp;ndash; Charlie starts writing phonetically (i.e. the same way I write Greek&amp;hellip;), moves on to super-proper-scientist style (following a &amp;ldquo;smartification&amp;rdquo; procedure) and finally falls back to his original style as he gradually reverts back.</description></item><item><title>Simpson's paradox and the horrors of unobserved confounders</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/simpson/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 18:46:56 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/simpson/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s assume you have collected data from a hospital, where some patients are given a medicine and some are not. No experimental procedure was followed, you just collected whatever was out there and you want to check if taking the medicine causes improvements in health. With a bit of notational abuse, you want to check the effect of $T \rightarrow Y$. $T$ can be either 0 or 1 (whether someone was treated or not using the medicine), while $Y$ is a measurement of life quality &amp;ndash; the higher the better.</description></item><item><title>Cookie cutter data science</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ccds/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 10:00:07 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ccds/</guid><description>I &amp;rsquo;ve recently discovered https://github.com/drivendata/cookiecutter-data-science/ &amp;ndash; an effort to standardise the pipeline of a data science project. The practices proposed seem ideal to me &amp;ndash; from a very sane directory structure to discussing makefiles as project pipeline DAGs.
Not sure how I managed to survive using completely custom project templates for each project. In fact, I will argue, one should go ahead and automate the whole report/presentation generation pipeline. There aren&amp;rsquo;t that many data science patterns anyway (let&amp;rsquo;s say regression/classification/causal inference/time-series analysis/arbitrary optimisation), so it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that hard.</description></item><item><title>Natural language interfaces for the command line and privacy</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/llmcmd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 06:15:54 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/llmcmd/</guid><description>Microsoft released a natural language interface for the command line (https://github.com/microsoft/Codex-CLI), while a past effort can been seen here: https://github.com/tom-doerr/zsh_codex. What I find worrying is that there is currently no way of using a local model &amp;mdash; these services do remote calls. Which means that you are bound to call OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s APIs, which pretty much guarantees loss of privacy. It looks like alternatives are doing much on the privacy front &amp;ndash; see here: https://www.</description></item><item><title>Mage: the themes</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 17:33:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</guid><description>I listen to podcasts mostly when I drive; I&amp;rsquo;ll compile a list at some point, but my top game-y podcast is definitely this: https://magethepodcast.com/
Mage is one of the most idealistic games you can play. There is no &amp;ldquo;concrete&amp;rdquo; reality, and the main theme of the game is one of self-discovery: you can be whatever you want to be. It flies on the face of my beliefs about the world, but the idea of changing the universe through thought is at the very least seductive.</description></item><item><title>Vale and atom</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/vale/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 10:54:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/vale/</guid><description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to get atomic-vale to work in atom (the editor). Took me a while; on top of a working vale installation, you need to install the linter plugins. From the command line do:
apm install linter The functionality vale provides is exceptionally good, and I am surprised I haven&amp;rsquo;t heard of this before &amp;ndash; I first read about it in hacker news post.</description></item><item><title>Large language models - GPT-3 this time</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 07:26:17 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp2/</guid><description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve started playing with GPT-3 this morning, posing the same questions I&amp;rsquo;ve asked GPT-J. Seems like the answers are much more coherent. For default configuration parameters I get reasonable stuff, but the model has no concept if something is real or not and makes things up:
&amp;ndash; Q: How do I make steel?
A: There are many ways to make steel. The most common method is to start with pig iron.</description></item><item><title>Crypto and paper money</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/crypto/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 22:29:57 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/crypto/</guid><description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve never managed to get my head around Web3 and crypto. What&amp;rsquo;s the value beyond creating Ponzi schemes and bubbles that paper money does not solve? The Canadian trucker&amp;rsquo;s case kind of proved that if the state does not want you transact, you don&amp;rsquo;t. Paper money is anonymous, easy to use and exchange, and needs very little training to use. More on this here: https://web3isgoinggreat.com/</description></item><item><title>Large language models</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 22:22:42 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/nlp/</guid><description>I really don&amp;rsquo;t get all that hype around large language models. I can understand their uses in NLP (and their superb transfer learning powers), but people are treating them like the end-goal of AI. I might be biased, but they don&amp;rsquo;t look that smart to me &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve tried this one here: https://6b.eleuther.ai/. You get different results based on what parameters you use, but:
Model with top-p = 1.0, temperature = 0 (i.</description></item><item><title>Labour theory of value through the lens of reinforcement learning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 07:09:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</guid><description>One of the popular online debates has been on the usefulness of the labour theory of value (LTV). I&amp;rsquo;ll attempt to give LTV a reinforcement learning (RL) spin (that&amp;rsquo;s how I understand it anyway) which should hopefully clarify things a bit. I&amp;rsquo;ll also abuse notation.
Imagine a scenario where an agent (an abstraction of a capitalist, firm, upper management etc) has access to the following at every time step $t$:</description></item><item><title>Goodhart’s Law and AI</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/goodheart/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 14:18:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/goodheart/</guid><description>OpenAI has a blog post here &amp;ndash; quoting from the article:
Goodhart’s law famously says: “When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.” Although originally from economics, it’s something we have to grapple with at OpenAI when figuring out how to optimize objectives that are difficult or costly to measure. It’s often necessary to introduce some proxy objective that’s easier or cheaper to measure, but when we do this, we need to be careful not to optimize it too much.</description></item><item><title>She was a phantom of delight</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 20:41:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</guid><description>William Wordsworth&amp;rsquo;s poem &amp;ldquo;She Was a Phantom of Delight&amp;rdquo; has gotten a new life through netflix third edition of &amp;ldquo;Love, Death and Robots&amp;rdquo;. The specific quote is:
And now I see with eye serene The very pulse of the machine; A Being breathing thoughtful breath, A Traveller between life and death; I originally thought the poem was about some kind of occult revelation the author had, but apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a love poem to his wife!</description></item><item><title>Financial times and workers' power</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 23:26:22 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</guid><description>The FT has published an excellent article Class war &amp;gt; rate hikes &amp;ndash; which concludes with:
In other words, inflation will subside, not because it’s necessarily transitory, but because workers don’t have the power to make it stick around.
What surprises me is how openly this is discussed. Instead of the &amp;ldquo;the euthanasia of the rentier&amp;rdquo;, we got the death of labour &amp;ndash; see the massive losses predicted by OECD below:</description></item><item><title>Coding the matrix</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/cm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 19:40:11 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/cm/</guid><description>I thoroughly admire efforts to turn mathematics into code &amp;ndash; in the legacy of Coding the Matrix. A new book is being released on the topic of Logic: Mathematical Logic through Python. Proof assistants (the likes of Lean) are being continuously developed and becoming more and more mainstream by the hour. I am pretty sure developments in these fronts will revolutionise the teaching of mathematics, making them accessible to whole groups of hobbyists, the same way that autodiff revolutionised ML.</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky III</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 21:16:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</guid><description>Rodney Stark in his book The Rise of Christianity, attempts to estimate the number of Christians per year, and comes up with a some figures that point to exponential growth. Bart Ehrman in the Triumph of Christianity disputes the numbers a bit, but again comes up with exponential growth figures. Incidently, Kautsky in his Foundations of Christianity discusses numbers, but mostly to claim that the Acts are exaggerating (i.e. the numbers are wrong :P).</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky II</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 18:01:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</guid><description>The debate between Kautsky and Lenin can be traced on/attributed to the revolutionary potential of the global north:
&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;Such is the position both in France and in Great Britain. Comrade Crispien does not regard the split like a Communist, but quite in the spirit of Kautsky, who is supposed to have no influence. Then Crispien went on to speak of high wages. The position in Germany, he said, is that the workers are quite well off compared with the workers in Russia or in general, in the East of Europe.</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 11:56:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading Mike Macnair&amp;rsquo;s Revolutionary Strategy: Marxism and the challenge of left unity, and it occurred to me there is a whole world out there of ideas and topics that could be helped by more formal analysis, and by that I mean a more rigorous approach to quantify the outcomes of each topic, the parameters that would go in it and the debates that it would spark. As a start, one can take the the Erfurt programme and start doing a formal/data science analysis on each constituent part of the programme.</description></item><item><title>Working remotely</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/remotework/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 21:32:40 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/remotework/</guid><description>A number of businesses seem to be enforcing a 5-days-a-week-back-to-the-office policy, and obviously some high profile resignations have taken place. Looking at the products I use, they seem to be designed by companies that had a remote work policy even before the pandemic, and somehow I doubt this is an accident.</description></item><item><title>The spirit of the interwebs</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/interwebs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 08:07:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/interwebs/</guid><description>There is a whole trend (and I think my website falls right into it) of 90&amp;rsquo;s/00&amp;rsquo;s tech nostalgia. Quite a few of us feel that the implicit promises of an interconnected world were broken and we need to go back to the prophets. A quick guide for creating your own website the same way you would do it 15 years ago is this one: Web revival. I like the goals of these movements, I am not sure I am convinced with the approach the author is taking.</description></item><item><title>The brick bible</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bb/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 07:38:12 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bb/</guid><description>I have two go-to websites when I need a quick, cheap laugh &amp;ndash; the first is one is the Brick Bible. The author/artist takes some of the more controversial parts of scripture and renders them (with commentary) to Lego scenes. The second website is the comment section of Motley Crue youtube videos (&amp;ldquo;Grills, grills, grills&amp;rdquo;).</description></item><item><title>Neats vs scruffies vs money</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/neats/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 06:05:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/neats/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve stumbled upon &amp;ldquo;What is the well dressed educator wearing now?&amp;rdquo;, an AI education article written in 1982, through a twitter thread. The article can be summed up as a commentary on whether one should pursue theoretical methods vs a more experimental approach (i.e. neats vs scruffies) and has been done to death since the article was written, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have much new to say. What astonished me is the actual focus on education.</description></item><item><title>Big data</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bigdata/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 09:31:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bigdata/</guid><description>Most interesting problems I have encountered in my real-life expeditions involve small data. Big data seems to me like a problem devised by certain tech companies and picked up as a trend by people that don&amp;rsquo;t need it, forcing them to use tools of extreme complexity, and as a result delaying project deployment.</description></item><item><title>Openspiel</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/openspiel/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 17:26:46 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/openspiel/</guid><description>I make use of the common data science frameworks for my everyday work (sklearn, pandas, tensorflow, seaborn and the like). For game-specific stuff I find Openspiel indispensable. It does everything in a very nice API &amp;ndash; from standard RL methods to LP solvers for normal form games to integration with a ton of languages.</description></item><item><title>Elites and class</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 11:53:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</guid><description>Not sure if this is Foucault&amp;rsquo;s fault or just a random historical trend, but I see more and more posts defining class not on material conditions (i.e. on the number of assets you own, amount of sex you have easy access to, disposable income, free time) but on cultural aspects (i.e. the way you sound when you talk, the kind of work you do). This is particularly prevalent among right-wing bloggers; somehow the idle classes have decided that the elites are overworked middle-class professionals and art school graduates.</description></item><item><title>Observational data and politics</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gorbi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 11:18:25 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gorbi/</guid><description>In the age old debate between socialism vs capitalism (the really existing ones, not whatever idealised versions are theoretically possible) empirical studies are sorely lacking. The debate is somewhat poisoned from the outset, as it does not help that people tend to use the word socialism to mean anything from the smallest welfare state to a fully planned economy, but let&amp;rsquo;s confine ourselves to USSR and friends for the scope of this discussion.</description></item><item><title>Eclipse Phase and optimism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 09:42:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</guid><description>The politics of eclipse phase (the game) play nicely as an exploration of a post-scarcity world, where humanity struggles to come to terms with the widespread availability of futuristic tech (makers, full AIs, full body augmentations), but material constraints are mostly not there. Similar themes emerge in Peter Frase&amp;rsquo;s four futures essay. Two binary variables (scarcity and equality) are flipped to create four different potential futures. What is interesting to me is that 10 years ago writers on the left were seriously discussing the prospects of a post-scarcity world.</description></item><item><title>Games and will appropriation</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 08:05:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</guid><description>I often wonder whether the fact that games were generally thought of as the quintessential analogue of intelligence is just due to their clear links with liberalism; you have an environment and you have agents that try to maximise some notion of reward in that environment. Life seems radically different (no clear rewards, no environmental resets, no fixed set of actions, no clear transition function), but most games provide a good abstraction for a competitive universe.</description></item><item><title>Blade runner's soundtrack</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/br/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 20:38:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/br/</guid><description>The composer of Blade Runner&amp;rsquo;s soundtrack, Vangelis, died a couple of days ago. I cannot think of a more iconic cyberpunk soundtrack then the score of the original 1982 film. As an interesting side fact, the story of the film is set to take place in 2019. It&amp;rsquo;s 2022 and still no androids&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Automation keeps being predicted</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/autom/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 06:42:54 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/autom/</guid><description>Automation fears in the 50s, found on twitter, see https://twitter.com/abenanav/status/1526854505136021505
McKinsey (the consultancy) has a job automation chart here, posted in 2016. There seems to be a lingering fear of automation, as this old New York Time article, amply named &amp;ldquo;Automation Puts Industry on Eve of Fantastic Robot Era; Its Effect on Workers Spurs Unions&amp;rsquo; Drive for Annual Wage&amp;rdquo; seems to imply. Notice how McKinsey speculates that managers are secure from automation, though I doubt this is for the right reasons.</description></item><item><title>In praise of idleness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/praise/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 07:02:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/praise/</guid><description>Early in my career, over a break, I approached a co-worker of mine and complained that all of my life&amp;rsquo;s problems were due to my relationship with work. I had watched Office Space the day before, still one of my favourite movies, and almost shed tears of joy seeing that others understood the very same concept, that most of the time we spend on work is meaningless. To my surprise I got back an answer along the lines of &amp;ldquo;what else is there to do in life?</description></item><item><title>Gnostic vs Orthodox</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:33:32 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</guid><description>Philip K. Dick&amp;rsquo;s Valis contains quite a bit of commentary that I find fundamental in understanding gnostic thought. Dick, in his interpretation of Gnosticism, points to an intellectual error for the fall of man (and hence our short lives of toil, pain and labour) rather than the usual orthodox position of moral failure. Interestingly enough, Dick created his own gnostic mythology (which reads like a modern version of the already bizarre gnostic cosmogony, replacing gods with aliens).</description></item><item><title>Virtuals vs Reals</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/va/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:25:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/va/</guid><description>An essay that has been making rounds since it was published is N.S. Lyons&amp;rsquo; Reality Honks Back. It discusses Canadian truckers and the divide between &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; workers (which make use of real-world tools tools) and &amp;ldquo;virtual&amp;rdquo; workers (which deal primarily in information). It contains a flawed effort to link the whole divide to Gnosticism &amp;ndash; it astonishes me that the only modern author that somehow got the Gnostics was P.K. Dick in Valis &amp;ndash; but beyond that the whole argument is very convincing.</description></item><item><title>Measures and fairness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 06:58:18 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mm/</guid><description>A superb article popped in my twitter feed called Measurement and Fairness. The article, as the title implies, deals with the imaginary quantities (e.g. teacher quality) and how operationalising them via actual measurements is where the problem of using metrics (I use the word interchangeably with &amp;ldquo;measures&amp;rdquo;) lies; in terms closer to AI/statistics, how to you link latent variables with observed variables. What strikes me is how fragile the notion of latent variable creation is; one can create whatever metric/measure they want, operationalise it in whatever way they think suits them and use enough force and propaganda to reshape the world according to their fiction.</description></item><item><title>Measures tend to become targets</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/metrics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 09:34:45 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/metrics/</guid><description>Most complaints about gaming a system can be traced back to Goodhart&amp;rsquo;s law, i.e. &amp;ldquo;when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure&amp;rdquo;. In the most trivial of scenarios, let us imagine that an oversight institution is created to measure the quality of teaching, and they come up with &amp;ldquo;average GPA&amp;rdquo;, which takes the mean of all student GPAs at a certain school. The minute this is measured and compiled in a table, someone will start ranking schools according to average GPA.</description></item><item><title>Adversus ludii, adversus ludos</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 16:15:06 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</guid><description>Quick self-bio I entered AI through games; I&amp;rsquo;ve started my PhD thinking roughly that if we manage to solve poker (or more generally, games of imperfection and/or incompleteness), we will manage to more or less solve the problem of AI; solving the problem of AI meant solving the problem of labour. Nobody would have to work, because machines would do all &amp;ndash; just need to solve &amp;ldquo;the problem of games&amp;rdquo; and all we would end up doing is playing games.</description></item><item><title>The comedic value of reviews</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:20:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</guid><description>I often find reviews of higher comedic value than the actual content that is being reviewed. As a kid I used to laugh to the point of tears reading music reviews, and as an adult (?) I still find stuff like Chapo Trap House&amp;rsquo; Wolf Warrior Movie Review eerily funny. Not sure how popular the genre of &amp;ldquo;imaginary reviews&amp;rdquo; (Stanislaw Lem might have popularised it with &amp;ldquo;A Perfect Vacuum&amp;rdquo;) actually is, but I can easily imagine a version where non-existent movies, poems, books, music and the like are reviewed, purely for a good laugh.</description></item><item><title>For and against liberalism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:15:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</guid><description>I was listening to General Intellect Unit&amp;rsquo;s latest episode on my way to work. They discuss &amp;ldquo;Designs for the Pluriverse&amp;rdquo;, by Arturo Escobar. I think their commentary on individualism vs traditionalism is spot on. The response to the modern problem of being alone, alienated and having lost your soul is obviously becoming part of a welcoming community; in contrast, idolising traditional societies seems to me to be a symptom of excessive alienation.</description></item><item><title>Red plenty</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/red_plenty/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:47:46 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/red_plenty/</guid><description>There is this online 12 year old discussion between Spufford and Cockshott on non-market economies and what-could-have-been in the USSR. Even if we could plan the economy to perfection, and this is a big if, I am not convinced it would lead to the kind of freedom most socialists have in mind. Ultimately, human salvation lies in the conditions of production, or as Aristotle would put it in his oft-quoted passage &amp;ldquo;There is only one condition in which we can imagine managers not needing subordinates, and masters not needing slaves.</description></item><item><title>First century sexuality</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:39:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</guid><description>There seems to be a period in the Roman world where all forms of sexuality that were not meant for procreation were frowned upon. The middle Stoics, early Christians, the Epicureans (yes&amp;hellip;), the Manichaeans views on sex can be summed up as &amp;ldquo;better to be avoided, if not do sparingly&amp;rdquo;. In early Christianity, there is ample evidence in the mainstream gospels (e.g. check Matthew and the sermon on the mount), supporting text (e.</description></item><item><title>D&amp;D/Warhammer 40K</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 08:36:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</guid><description>Since I don&amp;rsquo;t get to play tabletop that much (or at all) these days, I substitute with Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 and WH40K: Chaos Gate. Good enough, but obviously far away from the real thing&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Surveillance</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/surv/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 05:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/surv/</guid><description>The EU and UK governments are desperate for our data, and this has been the case for a while. I have no idea what they plan to do with it (most people&amp;rsquo;s lives are super boring, what kind of political dissent are they looking for?), but Briar, Matrix and Signal seem reasonable, sane alternatives.</description></item><item><title>Failed prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Sanctify them in the truth&amp;rdquo; (John 17:17) Tesla (the car business) recently published a video of its AI day giving a tour de force of modern artificial intelligence (AI) methods. From monte carlo tree search to simulation-based reasoning, Tesla is throwing every modern technique to the problem of self driving cars, coupled with possibly some of the best research scientists and engineers in the business. Yet, somehow, this is not enough; as another video mocking Tesla for its inability to produce a self-driving car points out, the promise of real-world AI delivering anything that would resemble its science fiction counterpart is astoundingly far.</description></item><item><title>Moving to Hugo</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/my-first-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 12:28:47 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/my-first-post/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to move my personal website to Hugo. Took a bit of time, but all good in the end</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://ssamot.me/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/about/</guid><description>Working hard&amp;hellip;
I am a senior lecturer in data science &amp;ndash; see here for my institutional website. My research focuses on broader AI themes; I&amp;rsquo;ve started as a game AI researcher, but my interests have since drifted towards out-of-distribution generalisation, robustness and causal inference, though I still maintain a healthy passion for games. I also enjoy thinking how to build new societal institutions and have a general fascination with religion.</description></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://ssamot.me/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/contact/</guid><description>For work related stuff you can e-mail me at my UoE address, for anything personal feel free to contact me at my personal address.</description></item><item><title>Publications</title><link>https://ssamot.me/publications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/publications/</guid><description>You can find most of my (academic) publications under my Google scholar profile.
[1] Michael Fairbank, Spyridon Samothrakis, and Luca Citi. Deep learning in target space. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 23:1--46, 2022. [2] Damian Machlanski, Spyridon Samothrakis, and Paul Clarke. Undersmoothing causal estimators with generative trees. arXiv preprint arXiv:2203.08570, 2022. [3] Spyridon Samothrakis. Artificial intelligence inspired methods for the allocation of common goods and services. Plos one, 16(9):e0257399, 2021. [4] Yogesh&amp;nbsp;K Dwivedi, Laurie Hughes, Elvira Ismagilova, Gert Aarts, Crispin Coombs, Tom Crick, Yanqing Duan, Rohita Dwivedi, John Edwards, Aled Eirug, et&amp;nbsp;al.</description></item></channel></rss>