<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Comedy on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/comedy/</link><description>Recent content in Comedy on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 20:07:35 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/comedy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dilbert</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/dilbert/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 20:07:35 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/dilbert/</guid><description>One of my favourite comic strips is Dilbert &amp;ndash; his HR takes are insanely good &amp;ndash; see here: https://dilbert.com/strip/2022-07-15. The most fundamental line of thought in AI is the direct link between intelligence and agency, and Dilbert is making fun of the typical game NPC, someone with no real role in the world apart from just existing. Acting with purpose is also one of the fundamental tenets of liberalism, which poses a conception of humanity as agents in a cosmic game.</description></item><item><title>The brick bible</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bb/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 07:38:12 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bb/</guid><description>I have two go-to websites when I need a quick, cheap laugh &amp;ndash; the first is one is the Brick Bible. The author/artist takes some of the more controversial parts of scripture and renders them (with commentary) to Lego scenes. The second website is the comment section of Motley Crue youtube videos (&amp;ldquo;Grills, grills, grills&amp;rdquo;).</description></item><item><title>The comedic value of reviews</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:20:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</guid><description>I often find reviews of higher comedic value than the actual content that is being reviewed. As a kid I used to laugh to the point of tears reading music reviews, and as an adult (?) I still find stuff like Chapo Trap House&amp;rsquo; Wolf Warrior Movie Review eerily funny. Not sure how popular the genre of &amp;ldquo;imaginary reviews&amp;rdquo; (Stanislaw Lem might have popularised it with &amp;ldquo;A Perfect Vacuum&amp;rdquo;) actually is, but I can easily imagine a version where non-existent movies, poems, books, music and the like are reviewed, purely for a good laugh.</description></item></channel></rss>