<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Prophecy on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/prophecy/</link><description>Recent content in Prophecy on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 07:19:13 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/prophecy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Newton's prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/newton/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 07:19:13 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/newton/</guid><description>Newton is well known for his alchemical and theological writings. There is a table in https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/593608.Isaac_Newton, a biography of Newton which I read almost 20 years ago, which summarises Neuton&amp;rsquo;s prophecies. They were apparently derived from a close reading of the Bible, and not by any form of revelation. It&amp;rsquo;s not clear to me how he came up with these dates, or if the table has any validity at all. Another set of dates is reported here: https://www.</description></item><item><title>Failed prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Sanctify them in the truth&amp;rdquo; (John 17:17) Tesla (the car business) recently published a video of its AI day giving a tour de force of modern artificial intelligence (AI) methods. From monte carlo tree search to simulation-based reasoning, Tesla is throwing every modern technique to the problem of self driving cars, coupled with possibly some of the best research scientists and engineers in the business. Yet, somehow, this is not enough; as another video mocking Tesla for its inability to produce a self-driving car points out, the promise of real-world AI delivering anything that would resemble its science fiction counterpart is astoundingly far.</description></item></channel></rss>