<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Politics on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/politics/</link><description>Recent content in Politics on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 10:09:04 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Happiness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/happy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 10:09:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/happy/</guid><description>There is this anecdote that John Stuart Mill used to ask adherents of certain political theories what immediate benefit they would gain if their favourite ideas were enacted. I am not sure this this is the right way to frame politics (or technology or science or anything else). The active pursuit of happiness is deeply individual, and I strongly agree with Castoriadis when he claims that (in The Imaginary Institution of Society):</description></item><item><title>Should we still wear sunscreen?</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/crisis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 20:00:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/crisis/</guid><description>There is this quote, in the now legendary Advice, like youth, probably just wasted on the young that goes to show how certain truths of the post 1945 consensus are not with us any more:
Accept certain inalienable truths: Prices will rise. Politicians will philander. You, too, will get old. And when you do, you&amp;rsquo;ll fantasize that when you were young, prices were reasonable, politicians were noble and children respected their elders.</description></item><item><title>Planning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/planning/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 22:50:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/planning/</guid><description>The market, as an abstraction of how we should live our lives, has emerged so victorious that even the thought of minor governmental interventions sounds the alarms of heresy. There is one arrow of time, and that is one of more liberalism, i.e. more market as the solution to everything, no other thoughts needed. Yet the tide is turning, and has been turning for a number of years, but without much in the process of actual results.</description></item></channel></rss>