<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Politics on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/politics/</link><description>Recent content in Politics on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 10:07:47 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Liberal contradictions</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/contraliber/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 10:07:47 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/contraliber/</guid><description>Quite often it seems to me that the modern left (of the liberal sort) has lost its ways completely. It has dissociated itself from the material basis of reality to such an extent it can do nothing more then quietly complain as life happens. It wishes for a world that cannot exist. See here:
Without enough Latvians, we won’t be Latvia’: eastern Europe’s shrinking population
The battle for births: how the far right are exploiting Italy’s ‘demographic winter’</description></item><item><title>The culture of make believe</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/cultmb/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 11:36:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/cultmb/</guid><description>Jensen, D. (2004). The culture of make believe. Chelsea Green Publishing. is a rather bizarre book (in the sense that it often reads as random thoughts put on a paper), in the anarcho-primitivist tradition, that more or less equates civilisation (&amp;ldquo;the dominant culture&amp;rdquo;) with an algorithm that is hell-bend on dominating everything and treats the living as means to an end, as objects. In other words, our culture is in a permanent state of sin.</description></item><item><title>ERPs, LLMs, resource planning and cybersyn</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/erp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 10:18:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/erp/</guid><description>There has been quite a lot written about cybersyn, and more is to come, but its technological promise IMHO has been achieved years ago. Every manufacturing company has an automated inventory recording system, almost all needs are calculated daily, orders are put forward and control is performed centrally. Add LLMs to the mix and we really have the &amp;ldquo;heart of the enterprise&amp;rdquo;. We have an entity that can communicate to the external world in a easy way tries to expand aggressively.</description></item><item><title>Financially broke elites and moral superiority</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ll/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 18:23:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ll/</guid><description>Combing through right-wing forums (yes, 4chans and youtubes), one can find a very strange take, where there is a claim that apparently modern liberal elites are penniless, but that does not somehow stop them from being elite! Young university graduates, most of whom have to work in some of the most meaningless and boring jobs known to man in a depressing corporate department, and who will never be able to afford a mortgage, are the actual decision makers of this world.</description></item><item><title>Losing your ethical core</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ethicalcore/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 17:50:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ethicalcore/</guid><description>Going back to Against the Protestant Gnostics, I can&amp;rsquo;t stop thinking that the collapse of mainline US Christianity takes place more or less at the same time as soviet collapse (late 80s). Quoting Zhivkov, the last Bulgarian communist leader: &amp;ldquo;In my memoirs I am smashing the whole of Marxist theory. Marxism is mere nonsense and I am the first one to say that it is completely wrong&amp;rdquo;. Both socialism and progressive liberalism lost their moral core, they became empty husks and mechanisms for people to accumulate power.</description></item><item><title>Protestants, gnostics and modern marxists</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/prognostic/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 08:05:56 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/prognostic/</guid><description>Against the Protestant Gnostics is a fascinating read. From Irenaeus onwards, whomever mainstream Christians do not like they label gnostic, but at the very least the author of this book goes into great lengths to support his position. Unlike Irenaeus, who delves deep into Gnostic mythology and cosmology, the author of &amp;ldquo;Against the Protestant Gnostics&amp;rdquo; uses the bible as source material. He sees the extreme individualisation and lack of community as the modern cardinal sin, very much in line with Christopher Lasch.</description></item><item><title>The ends do not justify the means</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ends/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 13:53:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ends/</guid><description>I find that the whole premise of the lord of the rings is that should you cause greater suffering to achieve some greater good, you end up with some form of greater evil &amp;ndash; the prime modern example being The Road to Terror Stalin and the Self-Destruction of the Bolsheviks, 1932-1939.
The antidote to this is slow, gradual, well thought-out movement. You introduce changes bit-by-bit, salami tacticing the problems you face as much as possible and moving the consensus.</description></item><item><title>Marx and family</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/marxf/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 13:57:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/marxf/</guid><description>Same quick quotes from https://www.marxists.org/archive/lafargue/1890/xx/marx.htm on Marx and family
He had a great talent for languages which his daughters inherited from him. He took up the study of Russian when he was already 50 years old, and although that language had no close affinity to any of the modern or ancient languages he knew, in six months he knew it well enough to derive pleasure from reading Russian poets and prose writers, his preference going to Pushkin, Gogol and Shchedrin</description></item><item><title>Culture and societal transformations</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/culture/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 09:59:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/culture/</guid><description>I stumbled upon Why we failed to approve the new Chilean constitution: the need for a cultural transformation this morning while browsing twitter. Quoting:
I cannot stop thinking about Pepe Mujica’s sentence in his documentary, “the most important transformation is not political, but cultural.” We failed to approve the new constitution because we haven’t addressed the need for a cultural transformation that would allow us to negotiate a new set of values with one another.</description></item><item><title>Power laws</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/pareto/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 13:18:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/pareto/</guid><description>Quoting Anderson, Philip W. &amp;ldquo;More is different: broken symmetry and the nature of the hierarchical structure of science.&amp;rdquo; Science 177.4047 (1972): 393-396.:
In closing, I offer two examples from economics of what I hope to have said. Marx said that quantitative differences become qualitative ones, but a dialogue in Paris in the 1920&amp;rsquo;s sums it up even more clearly: FITZGERALD: The rich are different from us. HEMINGWAY: Yes, they have more money.</description></item><item><title>The tyranny of numbers</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/tyranny/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 20:32:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/tyranny/</guid><description>A problem I keep coming back to is one of the first things one notices when trying to analyse social science data; it is hard to come up with any concrete conclusion &amp;ndash; or, conversely, it is easy to make up any story you want, and have your data confirm it. It&amp;rsquo;s trivial to keep adding confounders and claiming that &amp;ldquo;aha&amp;rdquo;, this is confounded by X, which behaves like this and that, which you did not take into account when doing the study.</description></item><item><title>Sinking ships and the wheel of history</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ships/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 07:22:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ships/</guid><description>Chappo trap house is reviewing Lachmann, Richard. First Class Passengers on a Sinking Ship: Elite Politics and the Decline of Great Powers. Verso Books, 2020. The book uses binary tables to make its arguments &amp;ndash; and it is a pleasure to read. An example is the one below. Notice how we have fewer samples than required to exhaust the search space. What I find interesting is how elite-heavy his account it.</description></item><item><title>Happiness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/happy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 10:09:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/happy/</guid><description>There is this anecdote that John Stuart Mill used to ask adherents of certain political theories what immediate benefit they would gain if their favourite ideas were enacted. I am not sure this is the right way to frame politics (or technology or science or anything else). The active pursuit of happiness is deeply individual, and I strongly agree with Castoriadis when he claims that (in The Imaginary Institution of Society):</description></item><item><title>Should we still wear sunscreen?</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/crisis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 20:00:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/crisis/</guid><description>There is this quote, in the now legendary Advice, like youth, probably just wasted on the young that goes to show how certain truths of the post 1945 consensus are not with us any more:
Accept certain inalienable truths: Prices will rise. Politicians will philander. You, too, will get old. And when you do, you&amp;rsquo;ll fantasize that when you were young, prices were reasonable, politicians were noble and children respected their elders.</description></item><item><title>Planning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/planning/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 22:50:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/planning/</guid><description>The market, as an abstraction of how we should live our lives, has emerged so victorious that even the thought of minor governmental interventions sounds the alarms of heresy. There is one arrow of time, and that is one of more liberalism, i.e. more market as the solution to everything, no other thoughts needed. Yet the tide is turning, and has been turning for a number of years, but without much in the process of actual results.</description></item></channel></rss>