<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Socialism on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/socialism/</link><description>Recent content in Socialism on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 07:49:23 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/socialism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Machines of propaganda and violence</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/propavio/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 07:49:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/propavio/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the most persisting beliefs I keep coming across is that the world will change because of some sort of excessive sinning by the societal elites, and the only action one needs to take is to expose this sinning. The argument goes something like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>(a) The elites sin excessively (they are too self-indulgent, do not care about anything but themselves, too hedonistic, clueless, sadistic, you-name-it)
(b) We will reveal the cruelty and moral decay of the elites (or the system they support) to everyone
(c) All will see how morally bankrupt the elites are and hence start some form of active resistance
(d) The end result of (a),(b) and (c) is political change and/or collapse.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Labour theory of value through the lens of reinforcement learning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 07:09:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the popular online debates has been on the usefulness of the labour theory of value (LTV). I&amp;rsquo;ll attempt to give LTV a reinforcement learning (RL) spin (that&amp;rsquo;s how I understand it anyway) which should hopefully clarify things a bit. I&amp;rsquo;ll also abuse notation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine a scenario where an agent (an abstraction of a capitalist, firm, upper management etc) has access to the following at every time step $t$:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>She was a phantom of delight</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 20:41:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</guid><description>&lt;p>William Wordsworth&amp;rsquo;s poem &lt;a href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/45550/she-was-a-phantom-of-delight">&amp;ldquo;She Was a Phantom of Delight&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> has gotten a new life through netflix third edition of &amp;ldquo;Love, Death and Robots&amp;rdquo;. The specific quote is:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>And now I see with eye serene &lt;br>
The very pulse of the machine; &lt;br>
A Being breathing thoughtful breath, &lt;br>
A Traveller between life and death; &lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I originally thought the poem was about some kind of occult revelation the author had, but apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a love poem to his wife!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Financial times and workers' power</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 23:26:22 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</guid><description>&lt;p>The FT has published an excellent article &lt;a href="https://www.ft.com/content/4e3327f5-473a-4e76-b04d-e5d884219deb">Class war &amp;gt; rate hikes&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; which concludes with:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In other words, inflation will subside, not because it’s necessarily transitory, but because workers don’t have the power to make it stick around.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>What surprises me is how openly this is discussed. Instead of the &amp;ldquo;the euthanasia of the rentier&amp;rdquo;, we got the death of labour &amp;ndash; see the massive losses predicted by OECD below:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky III</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 21:16:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</guid><description>&lt;p>Rodney Stark in his book &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_of_Christianity">The Rise of Christianity&lt;/a>, attempts to estimate the number of Christians per year, and comes up with a some figures that point to exponential growth. Bart Ehrman in the &lt;a href="https://www.bartehrman.com/the-triumph-of-christianity/">Triumph of Christianity&lt;/a> disputes the numbers a bit, but again comes up with exponential growth figures. Incidently, Kautsky in his &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/kautsky/1908/christ/">Foundations of Christianity&lt;/a> discusses numbers, but mostly to claim that the Acts are exaggerating (i.e. the numbers are wrong :P).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky II</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 18:01:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</guid><description>&lt;p>The debate between Kautsky and Lenin &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1920/jul/x03.htm">can be traced on/attributed to&lt;/a> the revolutionary potential of the global north:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;Such is the position both in France and in Great Britain. Comrade Crispien does not regard the split like a Communist, but quite in the spirit of Kautsky, who is supposed to have no influence. Then Crispien went on to speak of high wages. The position in Germany, he said, is that the workers are quite well off compared with the workers in Russia or in general, in the East of Europe. A revolution, as he sees it, can be made only if it does not worsen the workers’ conditions “too much”. Is it permissible, in a Communist Party, to speak in a tone like this, I ask? This is the language of counter-revolution. The standard of living in Russia is undoubtedly lower than in Germany, and when we established the dictatorship, this led to the workers beginning to go more hungry and to their conditions becoming even worse. The workers’ victory cannot be achieved without sacrifices, without a temporary deterioration of their conditions. We must tell the workers the very opposite of what Crispien has said. If, in desiring to prepare the workers for the dictatorship, one tells them that their conditions will not be worsened “too much”, one is losing sight of the main thing, namely, that it was by helping their “own” bourgeoisie to conquer and strangle the whole world by imperialist methods, with the aim of thereby ensuring better pay for themselves, that the labour aristocracy developed. &lt;strong>If the German workers now want to work for the revolution they must make sacrifices, and not be afraid to do so.&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 11:56:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8033846-revolutionary-strategy">Mike Macnair&amp;rsquo;s Revolutionary Strategy: Marxism and the challenge of left unity&lt;/a>, and it occurred to me there is a whole world out there of ideas and topics that could be helped by more formal analysis, and by that I mean a more rigorous approach to quantify the outcomes of each topic, the parameters that would go in it and the debates that it would spark. As a start, one can take &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/history/international/social-democracy/1891/erfurt-program.htm">the Erfurt programme&lt;/a> and start doing a formal/data science analysis on each constituent part of the programme. I&amp;rsquo;ve broken down the programme demands into categories and re-organised them so as as to make each demand more specific and explicit. Next to each demand I have included a relevant research question, plus whether or not the demand is currently met in the &amp;ldquo;broader&amp;rdquo; west.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>