<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Socialism on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/socialism/</link><description>Recent content in Socialism on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 07:09:59 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/socialism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Labour theory of value through the lens of reinforcement learning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 07:09:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ltv/</guid><description>One of the popular online debates has been on the usefulness of the labour theory of value (LTV). I&amp;rsquo;ll attempt to give LTV a reinforcement learning (RL) spin (that&amp;rsquo;s how I understand it anyway) which should hopefully clarify things a bit. I&amp;rsquo;ll also abuse notation.
Imagine a scenario where an agent (an abstraction of a capitalist, firm, upper management etc) has access to the following at every time step $t$:</description></item><item><title>She was a phantom of delight</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 20:41:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/eyes/</guid><description>William Wordsworth&amp;rsquo;s poem &amp;ldquo;She Was a Phantom of Delight&amp;rdquo; has gotten a new life through netflix third edition of &amp;ldquo;Love, Death and Robots&amp;rdquo;. The specific quote is:
And now I see with eye serene The very pulse of the machine; A Being breathing thoughtful breath, A Traveller between life and death; I originally thought the poem was about some kind of occult revelation the author had, but apparently is a love poem to his wife!</description></item><item><title>Financial times and workers' power</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 23:26:22 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ft/</guid><description>The FT has published an excellent article Class war &amp;gt; rate hikes &amp;ndash; which concludes with:
In other words, inflation will subside, not because it’s necessarily transitory, but because workers don’t have the power to make it stick around.
What surprises me is how openly this is discussed. Instead of the &amp;ldquo;the euthanasia of the rentier&amp;rdquo;, we got the death of labour &amp;ndash; see the massive losses predicted by OECD below:</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky III</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 21:16:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</guid><description>Rodney Stark in his book The Rise of Christianity, attempts to estimate the number of Christians per year, and comes up with a some figures that point to exponential growth. Bart Ehrman in the Triumph of Christianity disputes the numbers a bit, but again comes up with exponential growth figures. Incidently, Kautsky in his Foundations of Christianity discusses numbers, but mostly to claim that the Acts are exaggerating (i.e. the numbers are wrong :P).</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky II</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 18:01:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts2/</guid><description>The debate between Kautsky and Lenin can be traced on/attributed to the revolutionary potential of the global north:
&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;Such is the position both in France and in Great Britain. Comrade Crispien does not regard the split like a Communist, but quite in the spirit of Kautsky, who is supposed to have no influence. Then Crispien went on to speak of high wages. The position in Germany, he said, is that the workers are quite well off compared with the workers in Russia or in general, in the East of Europe.</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 11:56:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading Mike Macnair&amp;rsquo;s Revolutionary Strategy: Marxism and the challenge of left unity, and it occurred to me there is a whole world out there of ideas and topics that could be helped by more formal analysis, and by that I mean a more rigorous approach to quantify the outcomes of each topic, the parameters that would go in it and the debates that it would spark. As a start, one can take the the Erfurt programme and start doing a formal/data science analysis on each constituent part of the programme.</description></item></channel></rss>