<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Games on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/games/</link><description>Recent content in Games on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 09:04:18 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>RPGs and ethics</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/tsrethics/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 09:04:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/tsrethics/</guid><description>TSR (the games company, eventually taken over by Hasbro) had a rather interesting code of ethics that evolved over the years. For a full list see here, where I copied the image below; what I found interesting is how hard they are trying to appeal to a certain demographic (the middle class parents of the kids that are to play these games). While overall there are some sensible bits, a few parts can be at best described as state propaganda (&amp;ldquo;Law enforcement officers are always good guys&amp;rdquo;, found explicitly in later editions).</description></item><item><title>Warhammer 40K: Chaos Gate</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/wh40cg/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 22:31:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/wh40cg/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing quite a bit of Chaos Gate lately (whenever I find the time that is), and I realised I can&amp;rsquo;t beat the final boss. I blitzed through the game recycling a squad of four marines, never levelled up anybody else, and I don&amp;rsquo;t have any mid-game saves. Which means in order to complete the game, I need to go back and start again, something I really don&amp;rsquo;t have the patience for.</description></item><item><title>Mage: the themes</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 17:33:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</guid><description>I listen to podcasts mostly when I drive; I&amp;rsquo;ll compile a list at some point, but my top game-y podcast is definitely this: https://magethepodcast.com/
Mage is one of the most idealistic games you can play. There is no &amp;ldquo;concrete&amp;rdquo; reality, and the main theme of the game is one of self-discovery: you can be whatever you want to be. It flies on the face of my beliefs about the world, but the idea of changing the universe through thought is at the very least seductive.</description></item><item><title>Eclipse Phase and optimism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 09:42:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</guid><description>The politics of eclipse phase (the game) play nicely as an exploration of a post-scarcity world, where humanity struggles to come to terms with the widespread availability of futuristic tech (makers, full AIs, full body augmentations), but material constraints are mostly not there. Similar themes emerge in Peter Frase&amp;rsquo;s four futures essay. Two binary variables (scarcity and equality) are flipped to create four different potential futures. What is interesting to me is that 10 years ago writers on the left were seriously discussing the prospects of a post-scarcity world.</description></item><item><title>Games and will appropriation</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 08:05:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</guid><description>I often wonder whether the fact that games were generally thought of as the quintessential analogue of intelligence is just due to their clear links with liberalism; you have an environment and you have agents that try to maximise some notion of reward in that environment. Life seems radically different (no clear rewards, no environmental resets, no fixed set of actions, no clear transition function), but most games provide a good abstraction for a competitive universe.</description></item><item><title>Adversus ludii, adversus ludos</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 16:15:06 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</guid><description>Quick self-bio I entered AI through games; I&amp;rsquo;ve started my PhD thinking roughly that if we manage to solve poker (or more generally, games of imperfection and/or incompleteness), we will manage to more or less solve the problem of AI; solving the problem of AI meant solving the problem of labour. Nobody would have to work, because machines would do all &amp;ndash; just need to solve &amp;ldquo;the problem of games&amp;rdquo; and all we would end up doing is playing games.</description></item><item><title>D&amp;D/Warhammer 40K</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 08:36:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</guid><description>Since I don&amp;rsquo;t get to play tabletop that much (or at all) these days, I substitute with Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 and WH40K: Chaos Gate. Good enough, but obviously far away from the real thing&amp;hellip;</description></item></channel></rss>