<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Games on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/games/</link><description>Recent content in Games on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 08:05:48 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Games and will appropriation</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 08:05:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</guid><description>I often wonder whether the fact that games were generally thought of as the quintessential analogue of intelligence is just due to their clear links with liberalism; you have an environment and you have agents that try to maximise some notion of reward in that environment. Life seems radically different (no clear rewards, no environmental resets, no fixed set of actions, no clear transition function), but most games provide a good abstraction for a competitive universe.</description></item><item><title>Adversus ludii, adversus ludos</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 16:15:06 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</guid><description>Quick self-bio I entered AI through games; I&amp;rsquo;ve started my PhD thinking roughly that if we manage to solve poker (or more generally, games of imperfection and/or incompleteness), we will manage to more or less solve the problem of AI; solving the problem of AI meant solving the problem of labour. Nobody would have to work, because machines would do all &amp;ndash; just need to solve &amp;ldquo;the problem of games&amp;rdquo; and all we would end up doing is playing games.</description></item><item><title>D&amp;D/Warhammer 40K</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 08:36:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</guid><description>Since I don&amp;rsquo;t get to play tabletop that much (or at all) these days, I substitute with Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 and WH40K: Chaos Gate. Good enough, but obviously far away from the real thing&amp;hellip;</description></item></channel></rss>