<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Games on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/games/</link><description>Recent content in Games on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 07:51:52 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bloodbowl</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bloodbowl/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 07:51:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bloodbowl/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Took an interest in bloodbowl lately (both the computer and the board game), and I am collecting and building teams. I&amp;rsquo;ve compiled the table below, with the help of Claude and chatGPT, data collected from the official NAF ratings: &lt;a href="https://www.goonhammer.com/blood-bowl-state-of-the-competitive-meta-2025/"&gt;https://www.goonhammer.com/blood-bowl-state-of-the-competitive-meta-2025/&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s dubious whether or not the breakdowns make any sense or if imperial nobility and black orcs are bottom tier purely because they are part of the boxed set (and hence new players tend to be familiar and prefer them). I&amp;rsquo;ve put a pdf together &lt;a href="https://ssamot.me/blood_bowl_teams.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, with each team having a unique color, as I am not planning on paining them properly, at least not for the in-house friendly games I am planning.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Worlds without end</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/wwe/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 11:03:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/wwe/</guid><description>&lt;figure class="floatleft"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ssamot.me/wwe_shadowrun.jpg"
 alt="Worlds without end"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;Worlds without end&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am getting back my passion for sci-fi novels (gradually&amp;hellip;) and starting reading more Shadowrun stuff. The Earthdown/Shadowrun cross-over is superb, and points to a comment I discovered in reddit some time ago on why Shadowrun tech feels different. The timelines of the main players are measured in millennia (vs six months), and that allows them to do long term thinking (and hence deep research).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Basic storytelling</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/basic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 16:20:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/basic/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Basic storytelling has a very simple, yet compelling design &amp;ndash; see here:
&lt;a href="https://channel101.fandom.com/wiki/Story_Structure_101:_Super_Basic_Shit"&gt;https://channel101.fandom.com/wiki/Story_Structure_101:_Super_Basic_Shit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A character is in a zone of comfort,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But they want something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They enter an unfamiliar situation,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adapt to it,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get what they wanted,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay a heavy price for it,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then return to their familiar situation,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having changed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not that comfortable with this as the basic arc of life, it involves way too much luck, and can only work in a stable world where you can try and fail as many times as you like. I wonder if there is a book of stories (something like &lt;a href="https://enginepublishing.com/eureka-501-adventure-plots-to-inspire-game-masters"&gt;Eureka&lt;/a&gt;) where this arc is followed, but the hero fails miserably along the path. E.g. you can fail at point 4, failing to adapt to an unfamiliar situation. Point 5 is a nice place to fail as well, you adapt but you get nothing.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>RPGs and ethics</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/tsrethics/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 09:04:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/tsrethics/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TSR (the games company, eventually taken over by Hasbro) had a rather interesting code of ethics that evolved over the years. For &lt;a href="https://shaneplays.com/rpg-history-tsr-code-of-ethics-dd-comics-code-authority-rules/"&gt;a full list see here&lt;/a&gt;, where I copied the image below; what I found interesting is how hard they are trying to appeal to a certain demographic (the middle class parents of the kids that are to play these games). While overall there are some sensible bits, a few parts can be at best described as state propaganda (&amp;ldquo;Law enforcement officers are always good guys&amp;rdquo;, found explicitly in later editions). Notice also the very clean &amp;ldquo;good vs evil&amp;rdquo; dichotomy, which in practice means nothing &amp;ndash; everyone sees themselves as the good guys within their moral space. White wolf comes in later on and tries to get people to play the monsters (i.e. vampires, werewolfs, mages etc), but it&amp;rsquo;s the cool monster type of good ends/horrible means. IMHO, the potential of RPGs to deal with system dynamics (i.e. identifying how institutions shape us) is largely unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Warhammer 40K: Chaos Gate</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/wh40cg/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 22:31:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/wh40cg/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing quite a bit of Chaos Gate lately (whenever I find the time that is), and I realised I can&amp;rsquo;t beat the final boss. I blitzed through the game recycling a squad of four marines, never levelled up anybody else, and I don&amp;rsquo;t have any mid-game saves. Which means in order to complete the game, I need to go back and start again, something I really don&amp;rsquo;t have the patience for. These days we have youtube of course, so here&amp;rsquo;s the ending (spoilers&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mage: the themes</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 17:33:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mage/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I listen to podcasts mostly when I drive; I&amp;rsquo;ll compile a list at some point, but my top game-y podcast is definitely this: &lt;a href="https://magethepodcast.com/"&gt;https://magethepodcast.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;"&gt;
 &lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/k1GVaGNnlOA?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mage is one of the most idealistic games you can play. There is no &amp;ldquo;concrete&amp;rdquo; reality, and the main theme of the game is one of self-discovery: you can be whatever you want to be. It flies on the face of my beliefs about the world, but the idea of changing the universe through thought is at the very least seductive. As most post-80&amp;rsquo;s RPG, Mage is hugely optimistic about technological advancement. Following rapid post-war technological developments, it looked like soon all that would matter is &amp;ldquo;the word&amp;rdquo;. Forward 40 years, it&amp;rsquo;s clear this is not the case. It will take a while to wake up from this dream, but I am confident the world will change for the better because of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Eclipse Phase and optimism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 09:42:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class="floatleft"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ssamot.me/games/ep2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
 The politics of eclipse phase (the game) play nicely as an exploration of a post-scarcity world, where humanity struggles to come to terms with the widespread availability of futuristic tech (makers, full AIs, full body augmentations), but material constraints are mostly not there. Similar themes emerge in &lt;a href="http://www.peterfrase.com"&gt;Peter Frase&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://jacobinmag.com/2011/12/four-futures"&gt;four futures&lt;/a&gt; essay. Two binary variables (scarcity and equality) are flipped to create four different potential futures. What is interesting to me is that 10 years ago writers on the left were seriously discussing the prospects of a post-scarcity world. Globalisation had made production invisible and overly optimistic AI promises probably created a certain feeling at the time. This optimism is no longer there, and quite a bit of thinking needs to be done as to where we are in terms of production capacity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Games and will appropriation</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 08:05:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I often wonder whether the fact that games were generally thought of as the quintessential analogue of intelligence is just due to their clear links with liberalism; you have an environment and you have agents that try to maximise some notion of reward in that environment. Life seems radically different (no clear rewards, no environmental resets, no fixed set of actions, no clear transition function), but most games provide a good abstraction for a competitive universe. Nobody plays games were your first state is the most rewarding state &amp;ndash; rewards accumulate over time. You start as a horrible low life and you keep getting progressively refined as a player/agent to the point where you reach some far away game heaven, the land of high scores and opponent defeats. The traditional control paradigm had an inverse reward structure &amp;ndash; you start happy, but your environment tries to make you miserable, so you need to discover the right set of actions to remain stable. Mathematically, you end up with exactly the same solutions, it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of perception. More modern work sometimes does away with external rewards completely, and just assumes that an agent maximises some internal intrinsic reward.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Adversus ludii, adversus ludos</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 16:15:06 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="quick-self-bio"&gt;Quick self-bio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I entered AI through games; I&amp;rsquo;ve started my PhD thinking roughly that if we manage to solve poker (or more generally, games of imperfection and/or incompleteness), we will manage to more or less solve the problem of AI; solving the problem of AI meant solving the problem of labour. Nobody would have to work, because machines would do all &amp;ndash; just need to solve &amp;ldquo;the problem of games&amp;rdquo; and all we would end up doing is playing games.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>D&amp;D/Warhammer 40K</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 08:36:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Since I don&amp;rsquo;t get to play tabletop that much (or at all) these days, I substitute with &lt;a href="https://baldursgate3.game/"&gt;Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.chaosgate.com/"&gt;WH40K: Chaos Gate&lt;/a&gt;. Good enough, but obviously far away from the real thing&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>