<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Labour on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/labour/</link><description>Recent content in Labour on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 22:59:15 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/labour/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Scarcity is the scourge of freedom</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/scarcity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 22:59:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/scarcity/</guid><description>I came across this superb paper: Aronowitz, Stanley. “The Last Good Job in America.” Social Text, no. 51 (1997): 93–108. &amp;ndash; quoting:
&amp;hellip;among others, Robert Spiegelman, Herbert Marcuse, and Murray Bookchin have argued, scarcity is the scourge of freedom and, from the perspective of the rulers, must be artificially repro- duced to maintain the system of domination. Hence, working hours are longer, supervision-call it surveillance-more intense, accidents and injuries more frequent, and wages and salaries lower.</description></item><item><title>Technology and labour in the Roman world</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/techlabo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 07:11:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/techlabo/</guid><description>I am reading Robert M. Grant&amp;rsquo;s Augustus to Constantine: The Rise and Triumph of Christianity in the Roman World
A superb quote from the book, that links directly to how we conceive technology today is the following:
Generally speaking, technology either military or civil did not flourish in antiquity. Perhaps the existence of slavery blocked technological advance. Another cause is suggested by a story about Vespasian. Offered an invention for lifting stone columns at Rome, he rewarded the inventor but refused to use the device, stating that he had to &amp;ldquo;feed the poor&amp;rdquo; by providing employment.</description></item><item><title>Elites and class</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 11:53:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</guid><description>Not sure if this is Foucault&amp;rsquo;s fault or just a random historical trend, but I see more and more posts defining class not on material conditions (i.e. on the number of assets you own, amount of sex you have easy access to, disposable income, free time) but on cultural aspects (i.e. the way you sound when you talk, the kind of work you do). This is particularly prevalent among right-wing bloggers; somehow the idle classes have decided that the elites are overworked middle-class professionals and art school graduates.</description></item></channel></rss>