<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Labour on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/labour/</link><description>Recent content in Labour on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 20:03:16 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/labour/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Labour will not be automated</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/labour/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 20:03:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/labour/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Most of what is written about automation is not worth reading &amp;ndash; mostly patentable techno-utopian rubbish, but this newly released article actually gets it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quoting directly from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://jacobin.com/2023/08/post-work-socialism-is-a-tempting-illusion/"&gt;https://jacobin.com/2023/08/post-work-socialism-is-a-tempting-illusion/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, it is worth noting that automation can’t solve the necessary labor problem because (a) some kinds of necessary labor, like education and health care and childcare, cannot be fully automated; (b) some kinds of necessary labor, from construction to agriculture, might in principle be fully automatable but not in the near or even moderate-distance future; (c) many kinds of automation eliminate some tasks but create new ones that require human beings; and (d) machines have to be monitored and repaired, so even where machines do fully replace human beings, the necessary labor of maintenance remains.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Scarcity is the scourge of freedom</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/scarcity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 22:59:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/scarcity/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I came across this superb paper: &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/466649"&gt;Aronowitz, Stanley. “The Last Good Job in America.” Social Text, no. 51 (1997): 93–108.&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; quoting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;among others, Robert Spiegelman, Herbert
Marcuse, and Murray Bookchin have argued, scarcity is the scourge of
freedom and, from the perspective of the rulers, must be artificially repro-
duced to maintain the system of domination. Hence, working hours are
longer, supervision-call it surveillance-more intense, accidents and
injuries more frequent, and wages and salaries lower. Marx&amp;rsquo;s belief that
the more the worker produces the more he or she is diminished, enriching
only the owners, seems more relevant today than it did in 1844 when he
first wrote this&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Technology and labour in the Roman world</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/techlabo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 07:11:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/techlabo/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am reading Robert M. Grant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/2994761"&gt;Augustus to Constantine: The Rise and Triumph of Christianity in the Roman World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A superb quote from the book, that links directly to how we conceive technology today is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, technology either military or civil did not flourish in antiquity. Perhaps the existence of slavery blocked technological advance. Another cause is suggested by a story about Vespasian. Offered an invention for lifting stone columns at Rome, he rewarded the inventor but refused to use the device, stating that he had to &amp;ldquo;feed the poor&amp;rdquo; by providing employment.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Elites and class</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 11:53:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/elites/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Not sure if this is Foucault&amp;rsquo;s fault or just a random historical trend, but I see more and more posts defining class not on material conditions (i.e. on the number of assets you own, amount of sex you have easy access to, disposable income, free time) but on cultural aspects (i.e. the way you sound when you talk, the kind of work you do). This is particularly prevalent among right-wing bloggers; somehow the idle classes have decided that the elites are overworked middle-class professionals and art school graduates. What I find astonishing is that the same middle classes, while losing privileges and status like never before, quite often internalise this &amp;ldquo;elite&amp;rdquo; self-image and focus all their efforts on cultural issues of tertiary importance.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>