<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Philosophy on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in Philosophy on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 18:30:37 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Taking appearances seriously in machine learning</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/tas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 18:30:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/tas/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been attempting to kind of distil what are the basic claims made in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15864830-taking-appearance-seriously">Taking Appearance Seriously: The Dynamic Way of Seeing in Goethe and European Thought&lt;/a>. The authors claim that modern science is locked in the the Cartesian/Lockean tradition, and goes something like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Everything has a hidden &amp;ldquo;form&amp;rdquo; (in the neo-platonic sense) and a separate appearance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>All we can observe is the appearance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We can use various methods of statistical/mathematical thinking to discover the form from the appearance (this is where ML fits in).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>A example given in the book is hand-waving (literally!). The Cartesian understanding would have brain/mind breaking the procedure of observing hand-waving in two separate parts: one observing arms flaying around and one transforming this movement into a &amp;ldquo;hello&amp;rdquo; representation in the brain. Any gesture recognition software has this knowledge baked in. Now, what is being argued by the author is that this processing pathway does not exist &amp;ndash; we see &amp;ldquo;hello&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>directly&lt;/em>. I am not sure what to make of this or do with it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Experience</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/experience/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 22:47:18 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/experience/</guid><description>&lt;p>I was watching the video below by Christopher Isham &amp;ndash; not sure why he does not respond directly to the fundamental problem of religion; quite a few of us are unable to &lt;em>feel&lt;/em> or &lt;em>experience&lt;/em> any religious reality. I would be happy to accept personal revelations as facts, but there aren&amp;rsquo;t any.&lt;/p>


 
 &lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
 &lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9Ils9zNWaaw?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"
 >&lt;/iframe>
 &lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>