<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 11:18:25 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Observational data and politics</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gorbi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 11:18:25 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gorbi/</guid><description>In the age old debate between socialism vs capitalism (the really existing ones, not whatever idealised versions are theoretically possible) empirical studies are sorely lacking. The debate is somewhat poisoned from the outset, as it does not help that people tend to use the word socialism to mean anything from the smallest welfare state to a fully planned economy, but let&amp;rsquo;s confine ourselves to USSR and friends for the scope of this discussion.</description></item><item><title>Eclipse Phase and optimism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 09:42:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/hw/</guid><description>The politics of eclipse phase (the game) play nicely as an exploration of a post-scarcity world, where humanity struggles to come to terms with the widespread availability of futuristic tech (makers, full AIs, full body augmentations), but material constraints are mostly not there. Similar themes emerge in Peter Frase&amp;rsquo;s four futures essay. Two binary variables (scarcity and equality) are flipped to create four different potential futures. What is interesting to me is that 10 years ago writers on the left were seriously discussing the prospects of a post-scarcity world.</description></item><item><title>Games and will appropriation</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 08:05:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ga/</guid><description>I often wonder whether the fact that games were generally thought of as the quintessential analogue of intelligence is just due to their clear links with liberalism; you have an environment and you have agents that try to maximise some notion of reward in that environment. Life seems radically different (no clear rewards, no environmental resets, no fixed set of actions, no clear transition function), but most games provide a good abstraction for a competitive universe.</description></item><item><title>Blade runner's soundtrack</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/br/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 20:38:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/br/</guid><description>The composer of Blade Runner&amp;rsquo;s soundtrack, Vangelis, died a couple of days ago. I cannot think of a more iconic cyberpunk soundtrack then the score of the original 1982 film. As an interesting side fact, the story of the film is set to take place in 2019. It&amp;rsquo;s 2022 and still no androids&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Automation keeps being predicted</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/autom/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 06:42:54 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/autom/</guid><description>Automation fears in the 50s, found on twitter, see https://twitter.com/abenanav/status/1526854505136021505
McKinsey (the consultancy) has a job automation chart here, posted in 2016. There seems to be a lingering fear of automation, as this old New York Time article, amply named &amp;ldquo;Automation Puts Industry on Eve of Fantastic Robot Era; Its Effect on Workers Spurs Unions&amp;rsquo; Drive for Annual Wage&amp;rdquo; seems to imply. Notice how McKinsey speculates that managers are secure from automation, though I doubt this is for the right reasons.</description></item><item><title>In praise of idleness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/praise/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 07:02:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/praise/</guid><description>Early in my career, over a break, I approached a co-worker of mine and complained that all of my life&amp;rsquo;s problems were due to my relationship with work. I had watched Office Space the day before, still one of my favourite movies, and almost shed tears of joy seeing that others understood the very same concept, that most of the time we spend on work is meaningless. To my surprise I got back an answer along the lines of &amp;ldquo;what else is there to do in life?</description></item><item><title>Gnostic vs Orthodox</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:33:32 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</guid><description>Philip K. Dick&amp;rsquo;s Valis contains quite a bit of commentary that I find fundamental in understanding gnostic thought. Dick, in his interpretation of Gnosticism, points to an intellectual error for the fall of man (and hence our short lives of toil, pain and labour) rather than the usual orthodox position of moral failure. Interestingly enough, Dick created his own gnostic mythology (which reads like a modern version of the already bizarre gnostic cosmogony, replacing gods with aliens).</description></item><item><title>Virtuals vs Reals</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/va/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:25:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/va/</guid><description>An essay that has been making rounds since it was published is N.S. Lyons&amp;rsquo; Reality Honks Back. It discusses Canadian truckers and the divide between &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; workers (which make use of real-world tools tools) and &amp;ldquo;virtual&amp;rdquo; workers (which deal primarily in information). It contains a flawed effort to link the whole divide to Gnosticism &amp;ndash; it astonishes me that the only modern author that somehow got the Gnostics was P.K. Dick in Valis &amp;ndash; but beyond that the whole argument is very convincing.</description></item><item><title>Measures and fairness</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/mm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 06:58:18 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/mm/</guid><description>A superb article popped in my twitter feed called Measurement and Fairness. The article, as the title implies, deals with the imaginary quantities (e.g. teacher quality) and how operationalising them via actual measurements is where the problem of using metrics (I use the word interchangeably with &amp;ldquo;measures&amp;rdquo;) lies; in terms closer to AI/statistics, how to you link latent variables with observed variables. What strikes me is how fragile the notion of latent variable creation is; one can create whatever metric/measure they want, operationalise it in whatever way they think suits them and use enough force and propaganda to reshape the world according to their fiction.</description></item><item><title>Measures tend to become targets</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/metrics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 09:34:45 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/metrics/</guid><description>Most complaints about gaming a system can be traced back to Goodhart&amp;rsquo;s law, i.e. &amp;ldquo;when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure&amp;rdquo;. In the most trivial of scenarios, let us imagine that an oversight institution is created to measure the quality of teaching, and they come up with &amp;ldquo;average GPA&amp;rdquo;, which takes the mean of all student GPAs at a certain school. The minute this is measured and compiled in a table, someone will start ranking schools according to average GPA.</description></item><item><title>Adversus ludii, adversus ludos</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 16:15:06 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/adv_games/</guid><description>Quick self-bio I entered AI through games; I&amp;rsquo;ve started my PhD thinking roughly that if we manage to solve poker (or more generally, games of imperfection and/or incompleteness), we will manage to more or less solve the problem of AI; solving the problem of AI meant solving the problem of labour. Nobody would have to work, because machines would do all &amp;ndash; just need to solve &amp;ldquo;the problem of games&amp;rdquo; and all we would end up doing is playing games.</description></item><item><title>The comedic value of reviews</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:20:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/comedy/</guid><description>I often find reviews of higher comedic value than the actual content that is being reviewed. As a kid I used to laugh to the point of tears reading music reviews, and as an adult (?) I still find stuff like Chapo Trap House&amp;rsquo; Wolf Warrior Movie Review eerily funny. Not sure how popular the genre of &amp;ldquo;imaginary reviews&amp;rdquo; (Stanislaw Lem might have popularised it with &amp;ldquo;A Perfect Vacuum&amp;rdquo;) actually is, but I can easily imagine a version where non-existent movies, poems, books, music and the like are reviewed, purely for a good laugh.</description></item><item><title>For and against liberalism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:15:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</guid><description>I was listening to General Intellect Unit&amp;rsquo;s latest episode on my way to work. They discuss &amp;ldquo;Designs for the Pluriverse&amp;rdquo;, by Arturo Escobar. I think their commentary on individualism vs traditionalism is spot on. The response to the modern problem of being alone, alienated and having lost your soul is obviously becoming part of a welcoming community; in contrast, idolising traditional societies seems to me to be a symptom of excessive alienation.</description></item><item><title>Red plenty</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/red_plenty/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:47:46 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/red_plenty/</guid><description>There is this online 12 year old discussion between Spufford and Cockshott on non-market economies and what-could-have-been in the USSR. Even if we could plan the economy to perfection, and this is a big if, I am not convinced it would lead to the kind of freedom most socialists have in mind. Ultimately, human salvation lies in the conditions of production, or as Aristotle would put it in his oft-quoted passage &amp;ldquo;There is only one condition in which we can imagine managers not needing subordinates, and masters not needing slaves.</description></item><item><title>First century sexuality</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:39:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</guid><description>There seems to be a period in the Roman world where all forms of sexuality that were not meant for procreation were frowned upon. The middle Stoics, early Christians, the Epicureans (yes&amp;hellip;), the Manichaeans views on sex can be summed up as &amp;ldquo;better to be avoided, if not do sparingly&amp;rdquo;. In early Christianity, there is ample evidence in the mainstream gospels (e.g. check Matthew and the sermon on the mount), supporting text (e.</description></item><item><title>D&amp;D/Warhammer 40K</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 08:36:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/games/</guid><description>Since I don&amp;rsquo;t get to play tabletop that much (or at all) these days, I substitute with Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 and WH40K: Chaos Gate. Good enough, but obviously far away from the real thing&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Surveillance</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/surv/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 05:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/surv/</guid><description>The EU and UK governments are desperate for our data, and this has been the case for a while. I have no idea what they plan to do with it (most people&amp;rsquo;s lives are super boring, what kind of political dissent are they looking for?), but Briar, Matrix and Signal seem reasonable, sane alternatives.</description></item><item><title>Failed prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Sanctify them in the truth&amp;rdquo; (John 17:17) Tesla (the car business) recently published a video of its AI day giving a tour de force of modern artificial intelligence (AI) methods. From monte carlo tree search to simulation-based reasoning, Tesla is throwing every modern technique to the problem of self driving cars, coupled with possibly some of the best research scientists and engineers in the business. Yet, somehow, this is not enough; as another video mocking Tesla for its inability to produce a self-driving car points out, the promise of real-world AI delivering anything that would resemble its science fiction counterpart is astoundingly far.</description></item><item><title>Moving to Hugo</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/my-first-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 12:28:47 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/my-first-post/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to move my personal website to Hugo. Took a bit of time, but all good in the end</description></item></channel></rss>