<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Christianity on ssamot's website</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/christianity/</link><description>Recent content in Christianity on ssamot's website</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:39:03 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/christianity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>First century sexuality</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:39:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</guid><description>There seems to be a period in the Roman world where all forms of sexuality that were not meant for procreation were frowned upon. The middle Stoics, early Christians, the Epicureans (yes&amp;hellip;), the Manichaeans views on sex can be summed up as &amp;ldquo;better to be avoided, if not do sparingly&amp;rdquo;. In early Christianity, there is ample evidence in the mainstream gospels (e.g. check Matthew and the sermon on the mount), supporting text (e.</description></item><item><title>Failed prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Sanctify them in the truth&amp;rdquo; (John 17:17) Tesla (the car business) recently published a video of its AI day giving a tour de force of modern artificial intelligence (AI) methods. From monte carlo tree search to simulation-based reasoning, Tesla is throwing every modern technique to the problem of self driving cars, coupled with possibly some of the best research scientists and engineers in the business. Yet, somehow, this is not enough; as another video mocking Tesla for its inability to produce a self-driving car points out, the promise of real-world AI delivering anything that would resemble its science fiction counterpart is astoundingly far.</description></item></channel></rss>