<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Christianity on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/christianity/</link><description>Recent content in Christianity on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:33:32 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/christianity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Gnostic vs Orthodox</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:33:32 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/gnos/</guid><description>&lt;p>Philip K. Dick&amp;rsquo;s Valis contains quite a bit of commentary that I find fundamental in understanding gnostic thought. Dick, in his interpretation of Gnosticism, points to an &lt;em>intellectual&lt;/em> error for the fall of man (and hence our short lives of toil, pain and labour) rather than the usual orthodox position of &lt;em>moral&lt;/em> failure. Interestingly enough, Dick created his own gnostic mythology (which reads like a modern version of the already bizarre gnostic cosmogony, replacing gods with aliens). Two versions of the Gnostic creation myth are depicted Figure 1 &amp;ndash; they are extremely idealistic and more abstract the the biblical creation myth, which might point to early Gnostics being more of an esoteric cult.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>First century sexuality</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 06:39:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/sce/</guid><description>&lt;p>There seems to be a period in the Roman world where all forms of sexuality that were not meant for procreation were frowned upon. The middle Stoics, early Christians, the Epicureans (yes&amp;hellip;), the Manichaeans views on sex can be summed up as &amp;ldquo;better to be avoided, if not do sparingly&amp;rdquo;. In early Christianity, there is ample evidence in the mainstream gospels (e.g. check Matthew and the sermon on the mount), supporting text (e.g. the very weird opening story of the Shepherd of Hermas) and in the surrounding fan fiction (e.g. of the Acts of Thomas, the Acts of Thecla, both which are widely and vividly anti-sex); the &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; mode of operation is either celibacy or monogamy with the aim of procreation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Failed prophecies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:14:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/world/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="sanctify-them-in-the-truth-john-1717">&amp;ldquo;Sanctify them in the truth&amp;rdquo; (John 17:17)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Tesla (the car business) recently published a video of its &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j0z4FweCy4M">AI day&lt;/a> giving a tour de force of modern artificial intelligence (AI) methods. From monte carlo tree search to simulation-based reasoning, Tesla is throwing every modern technique to the problem of self driving cars, coupled with possibly some of the best research scientists and engineers in the business. Yet, somehow, this is not enough; as another &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mfharlIQ2qE">video mocking Tesla&lt;/a> for its inability to produce a self-driving car points out, the promise of real-world AI delivering anything that would resemble its science fiction counterpart is astoundingly far. The likes of self-driving cars, &lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/elon-musks-open-source-openai-were-working-on-a-robot-that-will-do-your-household-chores/">robotic maids and butlers&lt;/a>, robotic farm work, &lt;a href="https://qz.com/2016153/ai-promised-to-revolutionize-radiology-but-so-far-its-failing/">automated medical doctors&lt;/a>, robotic you-name-it are currently a pipe dream, and might remain so for the ages (more on this later). Tesla operates within the mantle of extreme technological optimism, an almost default positions given the level of change the world has seen since the industrial revolution. This level of optimism is not unique to Tesla &amp;ndash; the techno-social landscape has been a source of unparalleled optimism across the political spectrum. Living in a world without progress is beyond our ability even contemplate, but this might be exactly what we might be facing.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>