<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Liberalism on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/liberalism/</link><description>Recent content in Liberalism on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:15:37 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/liberalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>For and against liberalism</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 06:15:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/lib/</guid><description>&lt;p>I was listening to &lt;a href="http://generalintellectunit.net/">General Intellect Unit&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a> latest episode on my way to work. They discuss &amp;ldquo;Designs for the Pluriverse&amp;rdquo;, by Arturo Escobar. I think their commentary on individualism vs traditionalism is spot on. The response to the modern problem of being alone, alienated and having lost your soul is obviously becoming part of a welcoming community; in contrast, idolising traditional societies seems to me to be a symptom of &lt;strong>excessive&lt;/strong> alienation. We can&amp;rsquo;t even conceive what it would take so as not to be alienated and we are inventing a fantasy golden past to go back to. I think the clues for what would constitute a sane societal organisation would come from consciousness studies and the &amp;ldquo;differentiated yet integrated&amp;rdquo; approach they seem to be converging on. Using reinforcement learning as a more practical analogy, you would need to setup societies like &lt;a href="http://rbr.cs.umass.edu/camato/decpomdp/overview.htmlDEC-POMDPs">Dec-POMDPs&lt;/a>, where there is a clear alignment between the rewards of the group and the rewards of the individual. It is not clear to me what institutions are needed to achieve this.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>