<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Religion on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/religion/</link><description>Recent content in Religion on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 08:50:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/religion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Idealism and AI</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/idealism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 08:50:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/idealism/</guid><description>In the not so-long-ago (i.e. 10 years), it was common knowledge in AI circles that agents needed to be embedded within the world to be able to do anything useful. This proved to be harder than expected; it&amp;rsquo;s really hard to train robots to do anything, as there is a long tail of unexpected events that makes mincemeat of any concept of &amp;ldquo;abundant IID&amp;rdquo; data, and hence violates most ML algorithms basic data needs.</description></item><item><title>The demarcation problem</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/beliefs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 17:56:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/beliefs/</guid><description>Science is not so much a fixed set of beliefs (e.g. the Earth is a sphere, the stars are distant suns etc.) but rather a process for gaining knowledge using reasoning (in the form of mathematics, simulations etc.) and data to support certain claims. Quoting Boudry, Maarten (2020) Diagnosing Pseudoscience – by Getting Rid of The Demarcation Problem. URL:(accessed 2022-10-31). &amp;hellip;as Thomas Paine put it, because their theories have nothing to do with reality.</description></item><item><title>Blind faith</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/faith/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 09:29:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/faith/</guid><description>Religious studies have a quite a lot to say on the world around us, and progress more specifically. In an article termed When Prophecy Fails and Faith Persists: A Theoretical Overview, one can read the same lesson we find in Kuhn&amp;rsquo;s scientific revolutions book. It&amp;rsquo;s hard for people to change their minds, and religious movements that fail to predict the future can thrive as long as they keep proselytising. Quoting:</description></item><item><title>Machine-readable bibles</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bibles/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 10:08:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bibles/</guid><description>I was looking today for machine-readable bibles &amp;ndash; apparently tons of them are here: https://www.crosswire.org/sword/modules/ModDisp.jsp?modType=Bibles and there is a python library to process them here: https://pypi.org/project/pysword/. I was surprised how long it took me to actually find these resources &amp;ndash; I was expecting that a google search would reveal the truth (:P), but nope&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Theodicy and evil gods</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/theod/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 12:15:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/theod/</guid><description>I was reading this morning Law, Stephen. &amp;ldquo;The evil-god challenge.&amp;rdquo; Religious Studies 46.3 (2010): 353-373. and Stein, Edward. &amp;ldquo;God, the demon, and the status of theodicies.&amp;rdquo; American Philosophical Quarterly 27.2 (1990): 163-167..
What is being claimed, more or less, is that one can create negative theodicies (i.e. why the universe is ruled/has been created by an evil deity) as easily as positive ones. It looks to me that the problem dissolves if you just accept that the universe/God/whatever you want to call it has no inherent moral position (or that its moral position is evolving, see Jung&amp;rsquo;s Answer to Job).</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky III</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 21:16:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</guid><description>Rodney Stark in his book The Rise of Christianity, attempts to estimate the number of Christians per year, and comes up with a some figures that point to exponential growth. Bart Ehrman in the Triumph of Christianity disputes the numbers a bit, but again comes up with exponential growth figures. Incidently, Kautsky in his Foundations of Christianity discusses numbers, but mostly to claim that the Acts are exaggerating (i.e. the numbers are wrong :P).</description></item></channel></rss>