<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Religion on ssamot's heretical rumblings</title><link>https://ssamot.me/tags/religion/</link><description>Recent content in Religion on ssamot's heretical rumblings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Spyros Samothrakis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 19:46:41 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssamot.me/tags/religion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ellul</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/ellul/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 19:46:41 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/ellul/</guid><description>Quoting from Ellul&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The New Demons&amp;rdquo;
The remarkable thing is that, &amp;ldquo;while excluding the existence, the essence, the name and the reality of God, Jainism and Buddhism very soon become authentic religions.&amp;rdquo; The religionizing power is so strong that Christianity (which I am deeply convinced is antireligious) is finally engulfed and is progres­ sively transformed into a religion. Then the movement of scientific rationalism, extended by Marxist, materialistic rationalism, winds up recreating the religious in the world.</description></item><item><title>Apocalypse and AI</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/apo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 12:45:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/apo/</guid><description>To the extent that I can draw an analogy, there is a pretty clear pattern taking place in prophecy, and it goes something like this:
Mark / Matthew / Paul: Second coming in one generation, new earthly kingdom of justice ASAP Luke: The kingdom of God is within you John: It&amp;rsquo;s all gone wrong, nothing is clear, we only have the word to rely on, the devil (or his father?) rules this world Apocalypse: It will happen and you will all suffer and die Origen: Most meaningful progress is after our death anyway &amp;hellip; Church fathers: It has already happened, the Kingdom of God has arrived etc (i.</description></item><item><title>Machines of propaganda and violence</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/propavio/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 07:49:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/propavio/</guid><description>One of the most persisting beliefs I keep coming across is that the world will change because of some sort of excessive sinning by the societal elites, and the only action one needs to take is to expose this sinning. The argument goes something like this:
(a) The elites sin excessively (they are too self-indulgent, do not care about anything but themselves, too hedonistic, clueless, sadistic, you-name-it) (b) We will reveal the cruelty and moral decay of the elites (or the system they support) to everyone (c) All will see how morally bankrupt the elites are and hence start some form of active resistance (d) The end result of (a),(b) and (c) is political change and/or collapse.</description></item><item><title>Theodicies</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/theodicies/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 22:26:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/theodicies/</guid><description>Every single Theodicy I&amp;rsquo;ve come accross reads like some wild nonsense to me. They simply don&amp;rsquo;t make any sense, to the point arguing against them is futile. As an example (though there are plenty), look here: https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/process-theism/
If God asked you before the creation of the universe if you would agree to be part of a world that was not certain to be saved—where there was real adventure and real risk—what would you say?</description></item><item><title>Terry Pratchett vs Philip K. Dick</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/tpvsdick/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 08:52:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/tpvsdick/</guid><description>I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say here apart from posting two quotes from two of my favourite authors:
Terry Pratchett:
And sin, young man, is when you treat people as things. Including yourself. That’s what sin is.
Philip K. Dick:
We did not fall because of a moral error; we fell because of an intellectual error: that of taking the phenomenal world as real.</description></item><item><title>Idealism and AI</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/idealism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 08:50:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/idealism/</guid><description>In the not so-long-ago (i.e. 10 years), it was common knowledge in AI circles that agents needed to be embedded within the world to be able to do anything useful. This proved to be harder than expected; it&amp;rsquo;s really hard to train robots to do anything, as there is a long tail of unexpected events that makes mincemeat of any concept of &amp;ldquo;abundant IID&amp;rdquo; data, and hence violates most ML algorithms basic data needs.</description></item><item><title>The demarcation problem</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/beliefs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 17:56:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/beliefs/</guid><description>Science is not so much a fixed set of beliefs (e.g. the Earth is a sphere, the stars are distant suns etc.) but rather a process for gaining knowledge using reasoning (in the form of mathematics, simulations etc.) and data to support certain claims. Quoting Boudry, Maarten (2020) Diagnosing Pseudoscience – by Getting Rid of The Demarcation Problem. URL:(accessed 2022-10-31). &amp;hellip;as Thomas Paine put it, because their theories have nothing to do with reality.</description></item><item><title>Blind faith</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/faith/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 09:29:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/faith/</guid><description>Religious studies have a quite a lot to say on the world around us, and progress more specifically. In an article termed When Prophecy Fails and Faith Persists: A Theoretical Overview, one can read the same lesson we find in Kuhn&amp;rsquo;s scientific revolutions book. It&amp;rsquo;s hard for people to change their minds, and religious movements that fail to predict the future can thrive as long as they keep proselytising. Quoting:</description></item><item><title>Machine-readable bibles</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/bibles/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 10:08:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/bibles/</guid><description>I was looking today for machine-readable bibles &amp;ndash; apparently tons of them are here: https://www.crosswire.org/sword/modules/ModDisp.jsp?modType=Bibles and there is a python library to process them here: https://pypi.org/project/pysword/. I was surprised how long it took me to actually find these resources &amp;ndash; I was expecting that a google search would reveal the truth (:P), but nope&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Theodicy and evil gods</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/theod/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 12:15:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/theod/</guid><description>I was reading this morning Law, Stephen. &amp;ldquo;The evil-god challenge.&amp;rdquo; Religious Studies 46.3 (2010): 353-373. and Stein, Edward. &amp;ldquo;God, the demon, and the status of theodicies.&amp;rdquo; American Philosophical Quarterly 27.2 (1990): 163-167..
What is being claimed, more or less, is that one can create negative theodicies (i.e. why the universe is ruled/has been created by an evil deity) as easily as positive ones. It looks to me that the problem dissolves if you just accept that the universe/God/whatever you want to call it has no inherent moral position (or that its moral position is evolving, see Jung&amp;rsquo;s Answer to Job).</description></item><item><title>The renegade Kautsky III</title><link>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 21:16:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://ssamot.me/posts/kauts3/</guid><description>Rodney Stark in his book The Rise of Christianity, attempts to estimate the number of Christians per year, and comes up with a some figures that point to exponential growth. Bart Ehrman in the Triumph of Christianity disputes the numbers a bit, but again comes up with exponential growth figures. Incidently, Kautsky in his Foundations of Christianity discusses numbers, but mostly to claim that the Acts are exaggerating (i.e. the numbers are wrong :P).</description></item></channel></rss>